Heat. Heat. N.
[Music]
Hey,
hey,
[Music]
hey. Heat. Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to episode 249 of the Ask a
Bijit Show. I hope everybody is doing
fantastic. Let us see who all is there
on the live chat. This is a live chat
episode. It's a super chat episode after
hundreds of episodes after after
hundreds of hours of ask after thousands
of questions answered. I have turned on
the super chat today. So let's see how
that goes. Uh but let me see who all is
there on the live stream. I can see
Anime Ramshi Khim Subramanyam Lakshmanan
Bhavan Pranavony Nikl Sav Dha J Mr. Jam
cost of Mukharji again DG walkthroughs
Korish KB fate Vin Baron Zemo Pran Paul
from Kolkata Dipti Talle Aush Pande
Animeish again Spade Event Countdown
Arpita Shukla Liette Nikl Balyan Pranav
Vidi Manar Shri Ramchandra Namaha Asra
Crazy Brain Rishi Edtopia Shlesh Chri
Ritik Badia Really now Info King, Pearl
Gupta, Baba Abijit,
Chow, Arpit, Ilas Gaming, Rashmir,
Priyanchi, Sud Raja, Dil, Oscar Madison,
Rakshit Mishra, Jooshi, Tan Chandra, uh,
Jatin Aherwar, Mr. 88s, Sanida, Kumar,
Sharma, DGBHF, Caitana, Manuja, Kulib,
Johan, Geopolitical, Dubai from Indor,
Mr. Jam Krishna Ragunat from the
Surinamese Netherlands. Uh Spade uh
Sange Kumar again Adita Prem Chira Aasti
Vishal
Patro Magdum Aditya Prem Torres
Adja Biology Angelie Sha and lots and
lots of other people. So
uh let's going get going with the
questions. Uh I will prioritize live
what is it called super chats today. Uh
so people have told me in the past that
I should turn on super chats. The
quality is better because people who use
super chats are more serious about the
questions. Uh so let's see how it goes.
I have always turned off super chat so
that everybody gets the same
opportunity. But let's see how it goes.
I I am not opposed to having better
quality of questions. So if there are
super chats I will uh prioritize those
but as far as possible I will take
everyone's questions. So let's start
with the super chats that we have.
Utkash has asked this question. Thank
you for so much for the contribution.
West took 500 years to go from dark ages
to modern society. Why did we India not
reach modern age? We were prosperous and
scientific since 8,000 or so BC. But it
did not lead to large-scale industries,
guns and tanks, satellites, computers.
Okay, so this is a question I'm sure
lots of people have that why did India
not industrialize? Why did India not
have advanced technology etc. Here's the
deal my friends. India was the first
fully industrialized society. The
British de-industrialized us and our
historians don't teach us that. That's
why we are not aware of the fact that we
were a fully industrialized society. We
had every kind of industry imaginable in
India. We had ship building, we had uh
um you know tech textile industries, we
had arms manufacturing industries. uh
you know technologically we were so
incredibly uh advanced in comparison to
the rest of the world. Um the first uh I
mean the oldest iron smelting is found
in in southern India in in parts of
Tamil Nadu even Sri Lanka you know uh
what they call cerak steel or Damascus
steel is actually crucible steel that
was that is a technology that was
invented in India. We had ship building
going back thousands of years. There
were ships that were used in the
American civil war that were built in
India. When Vasco Dagama reached uh the
Cape of Good Hope, he was he thought
that he had the best ships in the world
and he was astonished to see Indian
ships on the coast of eastern Africa
that were like three times his size and
that was those are just regular Indian
ships and we had uh hydroengineering. We
had I mean every single industry you
could imagine was there in India. We had
our own economic system which was
different from what we have today.
totally different and um I mean if you
if you if you want to talk about
technology you look at the the the
harbor the dockyard in places like
Davira and Lothal etc in western India
which comes under the time period of the
Sarasati synindu phase of our our
history of our civilization and if you
look at the dockyards there the harbors
of those ports they are comparable
favorably comparable in in size and
quality to today's visha Putnham
dockyard which can harbor aircraft
carriers. So let's understand, let's put
the real history in context. We were
genuinely genuinely the first fully
industrialized civilization and the
British de-industrialized us so that
they could then turn us into you know uh
this juice box that they could suck off,
right? They wanted to extract everything
of value out of India. And if India was
more advanced than than the British than
than Britain and Europe then you know it
would have the other effects. So you
first de-industrialize the society you
impoverish the society and then you turn
it into something else that you that you
want want to make it turn it into. So uh
we were more advanced than the British
than the Europeans even when they
reached even when they reached here but
we never used our advancement
technological advancement and prosperity
uh in those you know for those purposes
like you know uh colonizing destroying
exploiting
uh we never did that and that's why we
were destroyed ourselves. So maybe we
can we could have perhaps learned a
thing or two from our oppressors right.
So we had large scale industries. We
discovered we invented gunpowder tanks.
We didn't have nobody had tanks 500
years ago, right? Nobody had satellites
500 years ago. Nobody had computers 500
years ago. If you go back 500 years, if
you go back to the
1600s, 1700s and you compare the state
of technological development and
industrialization of India, visa with
that of the UK or of of England and
other European uh kingdoms, we were
better at that time and it was not
because of the so-called mules or
whatever. It was our own thing that that
tra that you can trace back thousands of
years.
So we are not taught these things and
that's why we have these questions in
our mind and that's why Indians suffer
from this crushing inferiority
complex because our education system our
teachers our professors our textbooks
don't teach us the truth right that's
the
problem Mr. Sid says, "How to overcome
mobile addiction and develop a routine
in the world in a world where everything
is done through your phone, mails,
calls, chats, meetings,
etc. Okay, look
uh I can I can I mean I should answer
you straight to the point, right? Uh no
need no point sugaring what I should
say.
Let's understand why does this mobile
phone addiction happen in the first
place. You're not the only one to this
to whom this happens. I know per people
personally to whom this is this is an
ongoing for for whom this is an ongoing
issue. So what happens is you you lack
something you lack some purpose in life,
right? Maybe you have a job which
doesn't give you fulfillment. Maybe
you're doing something that doesn't give
you fulfillment. Maybe you're supposed
to be doing something else, but you're
not able to do
it. There is some kind of a a
hole in your existence. You there's a
lack of purpose. There's a lack of
meaning. Maybe it's your fault. Maybe
it's somebody else's fault. Maybe, you
know, the world has conspired against
you and not given you the path that you
should be on. And you're not happy. And
then what you do? You find the cell
phone, right? The mobile phone. Here it
is. Everybody has one of these little
things. You look in look at it and you
you have these all these apps Instagram
and whatever else. You scroll scroll
scroll and very quickly these these apps
that algorithms you know those those uh
those machines machine learning
algorithms they very quickly identify
what are the things that make you happy?
What are the things that please you?
What are the things that you search for?
What are the things that you spend time
watching? And they and it gives you more
and more of that and you keep on
watching and you g you get this dopamine
hit after dopamine hit after dopamine
been hit and you know you get hooked to
it. It's a pleasure machine and you you
keep on scrolling to to find the next
source of pleasure you know 60 seconds
60 seconds 60 seconds and after before
you realize 3 hours have gone four hours
have gone right. So that's how this
happens. Initially it's harmless but as
you spend more and more time every day
you will eventually after a few weeks
you find you spending 3 4 5 6 hours a
day on the phone and it's a disaster for
anybody. Imagine how much I mean it
fries your brain. It fries your mental
circuitry. It makes you unable to
experience real pleasure in life, real
happiness in life. That's what happens.
So that that's how it happens. That's
the mechanism by which it typically
happens. And it happens because there is
something missing in your life. Now
imagine you are a person who has an
obsession, who has a purpose, a cause, a
mission. When you're sleeping, you're
dreaming of that what I'm going to do
next day or what I've been doing. And
when you wake up, the first thing, the
first thought in your mind is let me go
and get to work. Let me get up and get
back to work because I need to do it.
It's an obsession. Nobody's forcing me
to do it. I I it's coming from inside.
When you have that that obsession, that
mission, when you have that sort of
meaning in life, you think this cell
phone will come in the way. It
won't. So, what's missing is a purpose,
a burning desire to do something in
life. When you have that these these
little things, these scrolling apps and
all they they become pointless,
worthless, and you no longer care about
them. So the the way to overcome this
addiction is to find something that is
stronger and more meaningful to you.
Right now you know the problem is that
by the time most of us are are out of
school, college, university, by the time
we are in our early 20s, most of us are
disillusioned with the world. We have
realized by the time that the world is
very different from what we imagine it
would be. As kids, we thought the world
is a wonderful place and we can do
whatever we want and we can rise to the
fullest extent of our potential and so
on. But by the time we reach our 20ies,
especially in a nation like India or
even anywhere else, you find that the
world you know it it doesn't allow you
to do things. It is it is very hard for
you to achieve what you want to achieve
unless you fight really really hard. And
so typically in India, let's say by the
time you're you know 20 you have your
first job, you find that it's something
you never wanted. This is never what I
wanted to do. I wanted to become a pilot
or I wanted to become so and so but look
at me I'm I'm sitting on a laptop in
front of a laptop in a cubicle and I'm
doing
spreadsheets or or whatever else it is
that you're doing. So you are
unhappy you did not get what you wanted
and you don't see a path through which
you can you know turn things around. So
you then get into these things and of
course these things I mean you do
everything through that you know your
emails your your phone calls your zoom
meetings. So that's the problem. The
solution is first of all you need to
reorient your attitude. Your attitude
should be very clear. There's a song by
Led Zeppelin. Nobody's fault but mine.
That's the attitude you should have.
Don't blame the world for what happened.
Don't blame your family. Don't blame
your siblings, your parents, your
spouse, your whoever. Don't blame your
superiors, your bosses, your teachers.
Don't blame anybody. Whatever happened
to you, you allowed it to
happen, right? So grab life by its
throat, by the scruff of its neck and
and and try your best to turn it around.
And when you try something hard and you
have some goal, some objective, some
purpose, this becomes meaningless.
That's become this becomes pointless.
You don't find that burning desire that
that passion or whatever you want to
call it. Or maybe you're not putting
100% in whatever you're doing. Put 100%.
When you do that, of course, it's not
it's easier said than done. Everybody
has the temptation to spend some time on
social media. Don't I have it? Of course
I have it. Sometimes they do it. But I
typically have other things that that
will pull me away and not allow me to do
that and waste my time there cuz I have
certain goals, objectives, mission,
whatever you want to call it. So once
you have that some some bigger thing,
something that's bigger than yourself,
something very big that you want to
achieve, then these things become
pointless. Find that thing in your life.
Everybody can find it. It's not
easy. Speaking saying all this to you is
very easy. Doing is very hard. But
you've got to find a way to do it. So
Mr. Sid, all the best. All the
best. Okay. Rik says, "Why India chose
peace over Pakistan occupied Kashmir to
avoid
sanctions?" See, you you should achieve
something. If you see Poke, we all want
it, right? This land, beautiful land,
the land of Rashikashup, our ancestral
ancient land, we want it back and it was
taken from us by treachery and so on. We
want it back. Sure. Um, but right now
perhaps was not the right time to do it
because see, we have external forces
that are way more powerful than us. If
India is a 6t tall strong guy, then when
China is 20t tall and the US is about 90
ft tall or 28t tall or whatever you want
to call it. H so when you're 6t tall and
you've got a guy who is 90 ft tall and
who doesn't want you to do this, you do
you think you will be able to get it
done? No, you can't. So this is not the
time perhaps to do it. You have to wait
for the right time. And if you sit
around doing nothing, the right time
will never come. So India has to grow.
India has to do the hard work, the dirty
work, the not so glamorous work, you
know, go get down in the dirt and work
really really hard for the next 20, 30
years until we are 30, 40t tall. Then
let's see what the big guys can do. When
you are a little little fella, you
should not have an attitude. You shut up
and do the work. Okay? Lift your
weights, do your work, grow, grow, grow,
build the muscles. And when you have the
muscles and when you have the heft,
that's when you talk. So right now, we
are the little guy compared to the US.
That's why we quietly chose peace. Okay,
it's a very harsh world out there. And
you have to be practical and
realistic. So that's why we chose it
right now. The Americans see the
Americans, they they see some value in
Pakistan. Pakistan is valuable for them.
They want Pakistan to keep existing. The
Chinese also see Pakistan the same way.
Okay. So the Americans and Chinese see
see eye to eye on this matter. Pakistan
they both agree America and China are
enemies but they both agree that
Pakistan should continue existing and
both are much more powerful than India.
In that situation if you're the leader
of the country you do the right thing
and not push it too
far. Okay. It's it's going to take
another 20 years. I hope I'm wrong. I
hope it happens next next week. But
realistically it is more likely that it
will take 20 years compared to three
three weeks or three months or three
years. But it will happen eventually if
we all work together to make this happen
and we can all contribute in some way in
our own way in our own
0.001% way all of us that's what needs
to
happen. Anu says is there a possibility
of a Muslim alliance consisting of
multiple Muslim countries attacking
India in this decade?
Um I think the only Muslim countries
that would that that see uh that uh have
that sort of attitude towards India are
uh Pakistan and and and
Turkey. The other major Muslim countries
see which are let's first ask ourselves
okay which are the major Islamic
countries Muslim countries in the
world. Okay we we already spoke about
Pakistan and Turkey. Fine let's put them
here. Okay they are sitting here. Now
who is here? Here we have Saudi Arabia,
major Islamic country, right? The home
of Mecca and Medina, the the holiest
sites uh in Islam. So you have Saudi
Arabia. You also have Persia, Iran, our
neighbor, well neighbor, historically
our neighbor, soon to be neighbor again.
Iran now that's another major Muslim
country. You also have nations like
Egypt, right? That's another part of the
Arabic world. And you have nations like
the UAE, uh, Oman, uh, Qatar, Qatar is
quite small and so on. You know, the
these are the nations that we can talk
about when it comes to the Muslim world.
And we also have on the other hand a
couple of other nations like uh,
Indonesia and Malaysia. Now, if you look
at a nation like Saudi Arabia, they are
on very good terms with us and they have
they they have no intention of of towing
the Pakistani or or Turkish line when it
comes to India. Saudi Arabia is a nation
that wants to modernize. It's a nation
that wants to be even more prosperous in
the 21st century. It knows that very
soon a post oil world will arrive when
oil is no longer as valuable it used to
be. And it wants, you know, friends and
allies in the neighborhood. And we are a
nation that's growing. We are a nation
that's going to be great again. Why
would they want us as their enemies? So
Saudi Arabia and India, we are on
excellent terms. the relationship is is
getting better as we speak. Saudi Arabia
want to participate in
this this idiotic uh scenario. Okay. Now
Iran, why would Iran want to antagonize
India and so on? We are not you know
best friends like you know hugging each
other every day or something like that.
But we are not enemies in any any
manner. We have reasonably good
relations India and Persia. Uh Iran
nowadays it's Iran. So Iran won't
participate in this nonsense. you the
UAE is is extremely good friends with
India. Why they would not do this? Uh
who else is there? Egypt. Now we have
good relations with with Egypt. We have
excellent relations with our Indonesian
cousins. U Malaysia so but not not
really terrible relations, right? Uh and
so on. So apart from Turkey and
Pakistan, no other Islamic nation uh
would even entertain the thought of of
forming some coalition against India.
They would laugh it off. What nonsense?
Please go somewhere else. Go find a
convention of of of insane people. Go to
an insane asylum. That's what they'll
say. So there's no possibility of this
happening. And it's thanks to the
leadership that we have had the past
decade that we have completely turned
around our relationship with all these
nations. uh in in 2010 of a relationship
with Saudi Arabia, with UAE, etc. that
there's nothing to write home about. But
look at how it is today. So awesome job.
Awesome
job. Chiraasi says, "Why is Trump so
desperate?" Look, you have to understand
Trump's
um
psychology. I have been watching Trump
for for a very long time.
Most people in India at least and even
around the world would not have paid
much attention to Trump before 2015 2016
right I have been watching Trump
essentially since since the year 2000
around the 2000s early 2000s so there
was this show TV show called the
apprentice and Trump was the main guy in
the apprentice it was all about him it
was about him interviewing doing a long
interview over multiple episodes of a
bunch of people who will and he will
eventually hire one person to work work
for him for the Trump corporation the
apprentice and if you watch the first
three or so seasons of the apprentice
it's the first two three seasons are
very raw very real very unscripted later
on it becomes very much more polished so
in those seasons you see the real Trump
how he is and if you see Trump in those
seasons you will understand the real
Trump who Trump really is people don't
change I'll tell you something I'm still
the person I was when I was 2 years
I've learned things. I've acquired
behaviors and mannerisms and whatnot.
But I'm at the core of my being still
the same person I was when that I was
when I was 2 years old. People don't
change. The core uh inherent qualities
of a person never change. So Trump is
still Trump. And if you watch Trump back
in the day, you will see that he was
this very vain person, very
self-centered person, me me, huge ego,
very egotistical person, very
self-centered person. Um and
uh he is very
capricious. He he vacasillates a lot. He
will say one thing one day, he will take
a 180°ree U-turn the next
day. Constantly contradicting
contradicting himself. and he uh he
trusts very often the wrong people. He
very often uh promotes the wrong people
and so on. So that's how he is. He is in
constant need of
validation from the world that I'm the
best, I'm the best, I'm the best. And he
has he he's you know he's very vain.
He's very self-centered. He's very
egotistic. He's very narcissistic and so
on. That's the kind of guy he is. But
overall, he's not a bad guy overall. So
now as president who is his constituency
his constituency is the people of the US
not the entire population of the US but
the MAGA voter base that's his core
constituency and he is he every day he
strives to to to gain their approval and
validation every single day. So
everything he does on the world stage on
the geopolitical stage it's to prove to
his to his people the MAGA voter that
they voted for the right guy and I'm the
best I'm the best president ever. I'm
the best president ever. I I don't know
how to speak like him but you know what
so um that's the deal. So and he wants
to take credit for everything whether he
has done something or not and he wants
to be remembered as the biggest baddest
greatest president in the US since
Abraham Lincoln essentially or or maybe
better than Abraham Lincoln maybe better
than George Washington also that sort of
thing that's what drives
him and that's why he he he exhibits the
behaviors that we see him exhibit you to
understand the guy you to understand him
to realize why he behaves the way he
does. Um, Nav Singh Bajad says, "Why
don't you go to Joe Rogan or Pierce
Morgan to give the Indian perspective?"
Well, I'm right here giving the Indian
perspective and let's make this channel
much bigger, right? So, uh, look, it's
not like you can just walk in there and
and go and talk to Joe Rogan. You've got
to be noticed, right? And he he he
should think that you're he he should
have you on the channel and so on.
is like that Piers Morgan also I suppose
if you know the right people and if you
let's say you know the right people you
have to go and you know request them put
put in a word for me that sort of thing
so listen I don't need any any white
man's
validation the the Indian perspective is
right here let's say that I am India's
ambassador to the world let's let's put
it put it that way right so yeah if if
I'm invited in the future I'll I'll be
happy to go but right now the
perspective comes comes from
here. But uh thank you for the
suggestion. I appreciate that. Nav G.
Animeh G says in the memory of the
passing away of Sri Jan Nikkar, can you
throw some light on how he challenged
the big bang theory and can you help us
understand his quasi quasi steady state
theory? Okay. Uh all right. All right.
Yeah. First of all, um Dr. Jen Nardle
passed away recently. uh very famous uh
physicist astrophysicist worked with uh
the great Fred Hy and uh put forth a
theory that was a challenger to the uh
big bang theory cosmology right so um I
can talk about the theory I don't know
his life and work in great detail the
one work that I know him for is the
quasi steady state theory right so what
was this theory so Jant Narikar in
association with Fred Hy another a
astrophysicist who Fred I know I
personally know Fred Hoy from childhood
because I read a couple of his science
fiction books one was called a and the
other one was called the black
cloud very very nice books I really like
those books so anyway Fred Hy and
Narliker Dr.
had proposed this theory, the quasi
steady state theory of the universe.
What this theory essentially says is
that the universe has always existed in
the shape and form that it currently
exists in. And it doesn't it's not a
it's not changing. It's not a changing
universe. It's a steady universe. It's
always been it's essentially infinite
infinitely old or something like that.
Uh so it's an unchanging universe. It
doesn't expand. It doesn't contract. It
stays the way it is. Essentially that's
the theory they had proposed. Right? Now
today if you look at astrophysical
astronomical observations you will find
what will you find in the universe you
will find that if you go into outer
space you'll find that there is there is
a glow in outer space uh in outer space
photons very ancient photons very
ancient light exists in the universe and
it's a it's at a very very cold
temperature about 2 point something uh
Kelvin which is like just just about two
2 point something Kelvin above absolute
zero so extremely cold light in
extremely redshifted light right that's
what that's one thing we observe so
there seems to be a background radiation
all across the universe whichever
direction you look in it's mostly the
same and it's very cold and very old and
very redshifted redshifted means the the
the photons the the the waves are
stretched out now why are they stretched
out is the question right why are these
waves stretched out Then another thing
you see when you observe far away
objects in the universe like galaxies
typically the the furthest objects you
can observe are
galaxies. Now let's say you're observing
a galaxy that is way way far away. H
maybe a billion light years away and
then you can do the measurements and in
any galaxy you will have every single
chem chemical element imaginable. You
will have iron, you will have copper,
you will have oxygen, nitrogen, helium,
hydrogen everything, right? And all of
these elements if you see their spectral
lines you know exactly where the
spectral lines are. You can I mean you
can do that in physics lab or chemistry
lab in college or in university. So you
know where the sodium lines are. You
know where the other lines are and so on
so forth. You know exactly what the
frequency is supposed to be. But when
you see the
frequencies of the same chemical
elements in far away galaxies you'll
find that these frequencies are shifted
towards the red end of the spectrum.
They are redshifted. The question is why
are they redshifted? Well, the answer is
very clear because the galaxies are
moving further and further away from us.
And the further a galaxy is, the faster
it's moving away from us. So, the
universe is clearly expanding. Far away
objects are moving away. And the further
an object is, the faster it's moving
away. So, the universe is expanding and
the expansion is accelerating. So, there
is clear unambiguous incontrovertible
evidence that the universe is expanding.
And the universe has a leftover glow of
radiation everywhere in every direction.
Something happened sometime which left
behind this radiation. What was it? And
why is it so cold today? So if the
universe is
expanding at a very rapid
pace then in the past it would have been
contracting. If you if you you know take
the clock backwards, the universe is
this big today. It's expanding. In the
past it would have been smaller. It
would have been contracting if if the
clock goes backwards. And this cold
radiation would have been hotter. Now
you take you exterpolate it backwards.
You reach a time about 13.7 13.8 billion
billion years before today where the
universe would have been a single
point. So the universe expanded out of a
essentially a very small point of almost
infinite energy and mass density, almost
infinite temperature. That's the big
bang. So the evidence that we have shows
us that the universe expanded out of a
very small point which is the big bang
theory. So Jant Narliker and Fred Hy
they proposed this quasi steady state
theory. I am not very familiar with the
theory. I've never been interested in
it. It's a failed theory. I'm sorry to
say sadly. Uh but I'm sure it was
relevant at some point in time. So you
need to propose
theories, theories that that match what
is known today, right? The observational
evidence that we have today, we need to
have theories that match it. In the
future, more evidence comes out that may
perhaps invalidate some theory which
happened to the quasi steady state
theory of of Hil and Narlicker. Uh so it
was not a challenge to the big bang
theory. It was at that time very little
was known about the universe. At that
time it was not known that there is this
afterglow of the big bang this cosmic
microwave background radiation that we
know of today. Pensas and Wilson
discovered it by mistake completely
accidentally and they completely
accidentally got a Nobel prize for that
and so on. So when they proposed this
theory it was a very good theory and it
was a theory that people took seriously
and the big bang theory at the time did
not have too many takers. It was not
even called the big bang theory. And
Narlicker's uh colleague collaborator
Fred Hy, he went on some radio show
because there was no TV back in the day.
He went on a radio show and to make fun
of this theory, he called it what the he
called it the big bang as a porative
remark but it got it stuck and today we
all call it the big bang theory. Uh so
that's what it was. His theory was that
the universe essentially is unchanging.
It's not expanding. It's not
contracting. It doesn't change much.
just stays the way it is and probably it
means that it's infinitely old or
something. That was a theory and it was
a a failed theory. I don't know what
other work Dr. Nardiker may have done.
I'm sure he was a great popularizer of
science. He was a great uh professor. He
was a great uh communicator and teacher
of science and so on. And uh yeah, so he
was definitely uh one of our great
physicists, astrophysicists. And uh I'm
sure the world is
poorer now that we have lost him. The
world is poorer for his passing. So
thank you Dr. Narika for everything you
did and we will remember you fondly.
Thank you sir. Right. Okay. Good
question. Vidi Manar is a new member.
Thank you so much ma'am. I really
appreciate it. Um geopolitical dub says
why is France so reluctant to share
source code? You see nobody will give
source code. Nobody will source code is
is the secret source the brains behind
um whatever m whatever the machine does.
So obviously uh geopolitical Dubai is
talking about the source code that
drives the
software which is at the heart of the
Rafal fighter plane. Let's say it's not
the Rafal, it's something else. The
source code is the heart. It's it's the
logic, right? So let's say you have a
fighter plane and today I'll tell you
something most uh fourth and fifth
generation fighter planes are inherently
unstable designs. So if you go back to
the Cessna planes you know what a Cessna
plane looks like. Let me put that on
screen so that you all you know um let's
let's go to the map. So you know
aircraft designs have evolved. So let's
say
Cessna Cesna aircraft. So your typical
Cessna aircraft looks like this. You
know, this sort of thing. Uh these are
your Cessna aircraft. We've all seen
these all over the place. You know, very
standard design. So these designs, these
aircraft designs are inherently stable.
If you switch off the engine, the plane
will just glide, glide, glide as long as
it is possible until it reaches stall
speed. But otherwise, it will just keep
on gliding. It's a very stable design.
If you look at uh designs like this
one, Spitfire, this was another pro
probably very very stable design. So you
switch off the air the engine, the plane
will just fly itself. It will refuse to
crash until it reaches stall speed. And
older aircraft had these stable designs.
Now if you look at the B20 B whatever
bomber uh stealth
bomber B2 stealth bomber, what is it? Is
it B2? Yeah, these things. This aircraft
has a shockingly unstable design. Okay,
if you switch off the power, it'll just
fall like a rock. The same goes for the
the ajis fighter plane. The fighter is
doesn't have a completely stable design.
And this is this unstable design is by
design. That's what makes it more
maneuverable. But then to stabilize the
aircraft when it's flying, you need a
software that controls all the control
surfaces and gets all the feedback in
real time from what's happening and it
keeps the system
stable. So there's a s there's a source
code that goes into that into the
stability of the aircraft. Then there's
source code for the target acquisition
system and source code for all kinds of
things. Now this this is is the heart of
everything and you would not share that.
That's I mean it it's do you have any
idea how difficult it is to write
software? I mean unless you you've
written software you will not know how
hard it is. You make one change in one
subsystem somewhere and it'll break 17
other things somewhere else and then
it's a you got to going to pull your
hair out trying to figure out what went
wrong. Debugging and god knows what.
Anybody who has written software will
understand that. So source code and and
typically the source code in these
systems, fighter planes, it goes to
millions of lines of code. It's
extremely complex. Why would you give it
up? I mean it's it's worth billions of
dollars, I'm sure, maybe more, maybe
tens of billions of dollars. So that's
why, you know, it's it's very very
hardearned whatever they have created
and it's
very you would not give it away. If we
we had a source code, I mean we have the
source of the code of the nobody wrote
it for us. We wrote it ourselves. It's a
pretty good achievement actually and we
would not give it away to anybody,
right? And so on. So nobody gives it
away. It's you can't blame them for it.
So at the end of the day, we have to
design our own aircraft systems. We can
buy things from others, but they will
not share everything. That's the
deal. Ashish Chri, thank you so much,
sir. Thank you very
much. AJ Sharma, thank you. Your view on
India sovereignty. We lost a few points,
have we? Earlier it was one now I
believe 0.8. eight.
Uh we were not able to destroy Pakistan
sovereignty entirely. Uh so yeah, that's
what happened in Operation Synindur, a
three three-day very quick rapid war and
we probably did not achieve everything
we wanted to achieve. I'm sure we wanted
to do a little bit more. I'm don't know
if the objective was to take back P at
this stage, but I'm sure we wanted to do
more. And I could see that from the
reaction of the prime minister in his
address to the nation that he was
visibly angry and probably he was angry
at Trump and clearly his reaction or
lack of reaction to Trump shows that he
is very displeased with Trump
interfering in the matter. Does it mean
that we have lost some sovereignty
points? Once again, let me remind you
all my friends of the definition of
sovereignty. So what does it mean to be
a sovereign nation? One, you have
complete control over your borders,
right?
You get to decide who comes in, who goes
out, and who can stay. That's number
one. Number two, complete control over
your economy. You control your economy.
You control your currency. Nobody else
does it. You don't have to accept
somebody else's currency as your
national currency. Right? Third, um, so
that's another definition. Thirdly, uh,
complete political independence. So you,
your government gets to decide the
policies that will be implemented in
your country and nobody else gets to
deci decide. That's another uh thing
about
sovereignty. Fourth, you don't serve
anybody else. You have complete control
over everything you do. Uh you're not a
mercenary nation like Pakistan. You're
not under foreign occupation. You you
don't host somebody else's military
bases on your soil. All these things are
are part of of of sovereignty. So if you
look at all these points put together,
we are completely 100% still sovereign.
Uh we were not able to completely
dismantle Pakistan sovereignty. The
Americans prevented us from doing it.
But we don't host American or any other
military bases on our soil. We have
complete control more or less for for
borders. There are some issues here and
there but overall we have control.
Everybody has some issues like that. Um
we completely control our economy. We
control our currency. We don't have to
use something like the euro or the
dollar or anything. Right? Uh we have
our own government. We don't serve any
other nation. So if you look at all of
this put together, we have complete
control over over our military. We are
not like the NATO nations who who give
up their the control over their military
to the NATO command and so on or we are
not like a nation like the EU where you
don't have your own currency and you
don't have your borders you know the
sanctity of your borders isn't there and
in the EU uh you have a situation where
Brussels decides what policies will be
implemented in your country and your
people have no choice in this that's a
lack of sovereignty we if you look at
all these things put together we are
still one on the sovereign scale. Yeah,
we we we were not allowed we were
prevented from u you know taking the
logic taking the operation against
Pakistan operation sindur the special
military operation to its logical
conclusion. Uh but we are still fully
sovereign. So I I I do not think it's
0.8. Let's not be so pessimistic my
friends. We are still a fully sovereign
nation but we can still certainly do
better and we need to work hard towards
that. Sanjay G, thank you very much.
Appreciate it. Taskar Gupta says, "Can
we use TV antennas all over India
combined together acting as a large
radar? Maybe some
changes."
Um, can we do that? I'm not really sure
how radars work. You know, I've never
really looked into it. Radars are
obviously, you know, what a radar does.
Okay, let's go back to first principles.
What does a radar do? A radar is a big
machine, let's say, with a certain
surface area and all that which emits
and also receives radio waves, right? It
sends out radio waves in all directions.
It it it turns like that 360°. It keeps
turning. It sends radio waves in all
directions. It also has a receiver to
try and catch those radio waves back. So
now radio waves travel at the speed of
light. Those are that's electromagnetic
radiation, right? Radio in the radio
frequency range. So they send radio
waves in all directions in a certain
frequency and there's also a receiver
that is listening to the same frequency.
Do I get something back in a similar way
and if I get something back it can kind
of tell where it came back from. So it
hit something and came back. So that's
how you can detect incoming aircraft and
other things. That's how radar works. Uh
now there are various kinds of radars
which work at various frequency ranges
and bands and all that um and so on. Now
does it mean that the larger your radar
is the more the better it is? I think we
have some radars that are pretty large
pretty large radars with a lot of energy
that they generate and such radars can
kind of detect stealth aircraft but
can't detect exactly where they are but
you can see you can see something is out
there. So can we use TV antennas? So TV
antennas are
receivers.
Understand a radar is not just a
receiver it's also a transmitter. It's a
transmitter and receiver at the same
time. So if we take TV antennas all
across India, we can create a very big
receiver. For example, when I was a
little kid, we only in India in the
1990s at before the 1999s also, uh we
only had one TV channel in India, Dur
Dash. And often the coverage would be
very patchy. So you would have an
antenna at the top in the top of your
house or whatever and you would have to
point it in a certain direction to get
good coverage and sometimes the wind
would blow it away and the coverage
would be bad. Sometimes the signal would
be bad. So what you could do is you
could take the antenna and plant it on
on top of a tree and then the tree
becomes a huge receiver and then you get
much better reception that sort of
thing. So it's so these TV antennas are
receivers. They're not transmitters.
So it can it can act as a big receiver
of various kinds of signals but it can't
act as as a radar. So I think your
thinking your thinking process is good
that you're trying to find solutions. Um
but it probably won't work in the way
that we want it to work as a very
powerful very large radar. But what you
can do is you can build dedicated radars
that are like know half a football field
size or maybe a football field size. You
can build it. It's very expensive can be
done and these can be very powerful. So
it can be
done. Arjuna says is it right to blame
in invarious rather than introspect?
Some time ago I I spoke about this song
by Led Zeppelin. Nobody's fault but
mine. You know you can blame invarious.
You can blame everybody but at the end
of the day it's nobody's fault but mine.
If if something bad happened to me to at
some level I allowed it to happen.
Invaders are invaders were terrible.
They were cruel. They were barbaric.
They were univilized. But hey, why
didn't we stop them? Why don't we
destroy them? So, you have to intros in
introspect. No question about it. So,
where did we go wrong? First of all,
when the Turk invasions happened, we
were not unified under a single
political system. We've had phases of
unification in the subcontinent, the
Moria Morian empire period where we were
united united under a single empire.
Before that, there was the Nanda Empire.
once again united under a single empire.
The Nanda Empire was so scary that the
Greeks ran away. Alexander's troops
rebelled. They mutinated. They refused
to go further into India. They went back
from from western Punjab. Right? So when
you are powerful, when you are united
like this, nobody can dare invade.
They'll be they'll be squashed. So
during the Nanda Empire period, during
the Chorian period period, nobody could
invade us. During the Kushan period,
they themselves were descendants of
invaders, but they were some of our
greatest emperors. Kaneshka the great
man. So during Kaneshka's time, nobody
dared look at India from an invader's
perspective. During the Gupta period,
some of our greatest emperors, the Gupta
emperors, nobody dared invade India,
right? When the Chola Empire was at its
peak in southern India, nobody dared
invade southern India. Of course, then
India was much harder to invade and so
on. So when you are not unified under a
single emperor who unifies the whole
subcontinent, you are at risk of
invasion. So that was the situation that
happened when the Turks first the Arabs
and the Turks invaded us. When Persia
fell to the Arabs, the Persians would
have wanted nothing more than India to
save them. But we were no longer under
the Gupta Empire at the time. We were
all fragmented by the time. So we could
not save Persia. If we had saved Persia
from falling to the Arabs, a lot of
things would not have
happened. So what you need is political
unity and political stability and you
need a highest quality of leadership.
when you don't have it, it's your fault.
You can't blame barbarians for being
barbarians, right? So, so the point is
not to blame our ancestors. You know,
this is a cyclical process. The rise and
fall of empires, imperial cycles, the
Chinese have seen it, we also see it.
Sometimes we are united under one
empire, sometimes we are fragmented. So,
when the fragmentation happens, it's not
really our fault. It happens. It's just
a natural process. And uh at that time
if somebody tries to invade it is for
somebody to rise up as a leader from the
fragmented kingdoms and unify the
country and fight the invaders didn't
happen and which is why we are where we
are today. So the point is not to blame
our ancestors not to blame the kings who
still fought who fought for centuries
who gave made incredible sacrifices. My
point is not to blame them. My point is
to learn the lessons today. Today we
have to learn the lessons that that we
have which we have learned from 1,000
years of very painful history. A
thousand years of humiliation. So
uh but listen it also is important to
blame the invaders for being utter
barbarians. In today's day day and age
it's all about propaganda right the
whole world tries to blame India for
having they say that India is is you
know what they say about India right?
They try to attack our culture, our
civilization and so on. You people have
a backward culture. You people have a
cast system. You people are
misogynistic. You people are backward.
Your culture is this, your culture is
that. So if you we are at the receiving
end of that completely unjustifiably, we
should also blame the invaders for being
utter barbarians. Whether the invaders
were brown as in the Arabs and Turks or
white as in the
Europeans, right? So, but we have to
learn the lessons of
history. Moit says, "Do you think the
reason the US is becoming hostile
towards India is due to us being the
same GDP as China in 2008 with much
better
demographics?" Now, somebody's thinking
here, aren't they? Moit, good job. See,
understand this, my friends. Moit is
absolutely right.
Um the US whether they say it or not
they will never say it but they regard
us as a potential future challenger
competitor potential future challenger
which means that maybe by a 2040 horizon
we may be the next big challenger the
way China is today and maybe we'll be
different from China and maybe we'll be
more dangerous perhaps than China from
their perspective. They don't want us to
be in that position to challenge them in
the future. Today we are a nice little
country. Not little but you know little
in terms of GDP and hard power compared
to
us. So we are like a cat. A house cat.
Well, you know what a house cat is like?
Nice cute little creature. It has claws.
It has teeth but it's relatively
harmless. It eats mice. It eats birds.
It can scratch you if you're annoying.
If it if it wants to be annoying, but
overall mostly harmless. But imagine
that house cat in 20 years becomes the
size of a cheetah or the size of a
leopard or the size of a tiger. Will the
house cat behave like a house cat or
will it behave like a tiger? Well, size
matters. And this nice little country
with a 4 trillion GDP, if it is a 20
trillion dollar GDP, it will not act
like a house cat, it'll act like a
goddamn tiger. And that's what they're
worried about, right? So, they will do
their best, my friends. The Americans
will do their best to keep us down. And
you can't blame them for it. They are
the top dog and the top dog wants to
remain the top dog and they don't want
any challenges to emerge down the line.
So they will do whatever it takes to
keep the potential challenger
down. That's the way a great power is
supposed to behave. So don't so there's
no right or wrong. There's no morality
or lack of morality in this. It's simply
the way the world works. It's a real
politic. Right? So the point is you have
to expect this to happen. The Americans
will increasingly behave like this
towards us and you know for when it
comes to India they may actually see eye
to eye with China and they may cooperate
with China when it comes to matters
concerning India they may cooperate with
Pakistan in matters compar concerning
India.
So you have to expect this and we have
to find ways to grow despite this issue.
But Moit is absolutely right. You have
hit the head the nail on the head
sir. Okay. PLTP says why crown agents
run RBI Indian media. Is it possible
that both governments is it possible
both governments work for the same
people? Why BIS Crown Temple in city of
London can't be sued?
Crown agents run the Reserve Bank of
India. The Indian media, I'm not sure
about the Reserve Bank of India, but the
Indian media is full of foreign agents
and
our our ancient elite, not ancient
elite, but postindependence elites of of
of India, the people who run ran the
show, ran ran the media, ran the
government. These were all Angloiles.
These were all people who had whose
families had essentially benefited from
British rule. Look look at this. Look at
it this way, my
friends. Anybody who in 1947 was
rich could only be rich because they
cooperated with the British. I think
that should be a no-brainer for
everybody. Any person, any any
individual or family or business entity
that was rich in 1947 when the whole
country was
devastated, they could only be rich
because they had cooperated with the
British. They had collaborated with the
British, which means they were British
agents. Anybody who was put in power in
1947 would be a British
collaborator. Okay?
uh and these people they controlled
everything in India for decades. So even
today you see the legacy of that you see
a lot of that I'll not go into the
details but you see that I mean a lot of
the Indian media for decades was
controlled by Brit people who are very
very favorably inclined towards the
British towards the west and who still
yearned for British
rule. I've seen YouTube videos of of
various restaurant owners in certain
parts of Mumbai which was then called
Bombay who have the a portrait of the
British queen on the walls of their
restaurants and who yearned for the
British to come back. Okay, there are
people like that. There are people like
that even today. The people with the old
money because see in 1857 all the true
Indians were killed off. All the true
Indian royal families were wiped out.
the ones that fought the British. The
ones that collaborated with the British
were given special
titles. So after 1857 only those who
collaborated with the British and served
British interests were allowed to
succeed and these
people they continued being being the
elites of India post
1947. So I'm not sure about the RBI but
the Indian media is full of the
descendants of these people. Okay. Um so
yeah that's a situation that that's why
I say that we are not decolonized we are
still very strongly
colonized until we get rid of the the
old colonial
influence you know things uh won't
really change and India won't really
progress I'm not sure about the crown
temple in city of London how we can sue
them and all but you have brought out an
interesting important point uh so yeah a
lot of very important positions in India
are still filled by these things. Okay,
Matthew Perez says, "Thank you for
recommending Children of Time. I've read
that in the Children of Ruin. Like that
even more. And I'm Children Memory.
Afterwards, I'm going to do Final
Architecture series." Okay, I haven't
read that. But yeah, uh these three
books are tremendous. I haven't yet got
on to the Children of Time or the
Children of Memory. H sorry, I haven't
read Children of Ruin or the Children of
Memory, but Children of Time was
amazing. The the spiders, right? the
story with with the spiders. Very very
interesting book. After a long time, I
read a science fiction book that I
really enjoyed. A modern science fiction
writer who writes well, very rare. So
yeah, I enjoyed it. And the final
architecture series. Okay, maybe that's
something I should find some time to
read about. So appreciate it, Mateo.
Very, very much so. Thank you.
Chola Empire says, "You once said
Indians are overly emotional about
Israelis and get and get praised mainly
for engagement, but Israelis have raised
issues like Bangladeshi Hindus and Palam
unprompted. Do you still hold that view
or has it
changed?" Look, anybody who
uh supports India online when we need
support and unprompted I appreciate
that, right? But let's understand we
should not get overly emotional about
anything. I appreciate anybody who
stands by my people in my
country because see my people in my
country are on the right side of things.
We are not evil people. We are not an
evil country. We are not colonizers. We
not occupiers. We don't occupy someone's
territory. We don't genocide people. Uh
we don't plunder other people's uh
resources. We don't do any of these
things. And so if people stand with us,
I I welcome it and I thank them for it.
Uh but please understand one thing that
the only flag you should have on your
profiles is your own flag. You cannot
have other people's flags on your
profiles and uh you cannot hero worship
other nations.
So I I I'm grateful for those Israelis
who did stand with India and uh yeah so
so I certainly have that view and
overall I am I'm very uh it's a Israel
is a nation I respect a lot and there's
a lot India can learn from Israel and
there's a lot of convergence of
interests when it comes to India and
Israel. So I would like to see the India
Israel relationship gets stronger and
stronger for sure. But I am not somebody
who will be overly emotional about other
countries. I welcome their friendship
and I welcome their respect and I
respect them back and that's how it
should be. More than that I don't
understand why people have to give more
than that. You know full supports are my
your flag on my profile. Why? I have
some selfrespect.
User 6362 says, "Why is the US selling
fighter jets to Turkey desri despite
Israel's objections? Is it because Trump
wants to reduce Russia's access to the
Mediterranean
Sea? Look u you see Turkey is an
interesting nation. Let's take a look at
the map. We haven't seen the map today.
Well, we'll break it out now. Let's
understand the geography of the region
because that kind of tells its own
story. So, here we are. Here we are. So
we go to Israel to the the Mediterranean
region and here we have
Israel. Now Israel is not far from
Turkey. You know you cross Cyprus and
you reach Turkey north of the
Mediterranean Sea. Um now why is Turkey
so important geographically and
geopolitically? Because it controls the
Turkish straits. the straight of
Bosphorus which is over here.
Okay, this is the straight of
Bosphorus and then there is the straight
of the Dardels over
here. Okay, this is called the Dardell
straight. These are two extremely
important choke points. You see, if you
have, let's say, a fleet of ships in the
Black Sea and you want to reach the
Mediterranean Sea, you have to go
through both choke points in the
straight of Bosphorus. It essentially
passes right through Istanbul,
Constantinople. And there are a couple
of bridges from which you have to you
can see the ships crossing the straight.
And it's a requirement that any naval
ship that crosses the straight is
required to show itself. So if you have
a submarine that wants to cross the
street, it has to show itself. It cannot
cross the street hidden. It's a
requirement. Okay? It's by uh by by law.
So this nation Turkey, it straddles
these two extremely vital straits, choke
points and that's why it's so important.
So Turkey has been rent seeking its
geographical location. So anytime Russia
which has the Black Sea fleet wants to
give its o its warships access to the
Mediterranean Sea it has to pass through
Turkey to through the Turkish straits.
Anytime it's its ships want to enter the
Black Sea from the Mediterranean they
again have to pass through the two
Turkish straits and the and the sea of
Marmara. So it's very very strategically
important this location that Turkey
occupies and it has been rent seeking
this location ever since uh yeah ever
since the second world war ended
essentially. So Turkey is very important
and you have uh what's his name Mr.
Erdogan who has these neo imperial
neotomantoman ambitions and he's playing
not just double game he's playing
multiple games. So he is uh to some
extent being friendly with with Moscow,
to some extent being friendly with
Washington. He's hosting US nuclear
weapons and warheads on his territory
allegedly, right? He is part of Turkey
is part of NATO. They've they have tried
to be part of the EU and so on. But uh
and and but they also have purchased the
Russian
S400 air defense system which is why
they were denied u participation in the
F-35 program and so on. So Turkey
because of its geographical location is
really important okay for NATO for for
the US. Now
uh Turkey and Israel obviously have
issues right because Turkey supports the
Palestinians and so on but they also see
eye to eye when it comes to Azarbaijan
because Israel and Turkey both support
Azarbaijan while India supports Armenia
and Turkey and Israel are enemies of
Armenia and so on and there are
different they have very different
reasons for supporting Azarbaijan but
that's that's a different matter. So now
why is the US selling fighter jets to
Turkey? Israel won't like it, but the US
has its own calculations and as far as
long as the sale of fighter jets to
Turkey doesn't really hurt Israel, it's
okay because Israel's national interest
is very important to the US. Okay. U so
it means that it doesn't really hurt
Israel's national interest. So
u so Turkey can certainly control the
extent to which Russia can access the
Mediterranean Sea and if required it can
if if Turkey wants it can even deny
Russia access to the Mediterranean
Mediterranean Sea. So the US wants
Turkey on its side right they don't want
to have physical occupation of Turkey by
invading Turkey let's just uh keep the
Turks happy and have them do what they
what we want them to do. So yeah, that's
the game and that's the game the US is
playing. Okay. Animeish says, "Are
rumors about Rafal source code true? Did
the French do us the same the US did to
the Os? Did they render Rafal useless in
this war with Pakistan? Is it an
effective plane?" Well, I have heard no
such rumors. I I'm not sure if if any of
this is true. I've not heard such
rumors.
Uh the source code issue
um look if there was an issue with the
Rafal source code it would have been
evident when we were trying out the
aircraft we have purchased the aircraft
what some years ago we've had it since
at least we've had a few aircraft the
first few aircraft ever since 2022 or
something or 23 I'm not sure which year
so we've had these aircraft for at least
2 three years and if there were issues
with their source code they would have
been very apparent from the very
beginning right um is it possible for
them to retrospectively in the future at
a future date disable certain sub some
systems it's certainly possible so
theoretically it's possible that I buy a
plane in 2022 it works fine but the day
in 2025 I need to use it for a for a war
suddenly some things don't work it's
possible it is possible I'm not saying
it it's what happened but theoretically
it's very possible
So theoretically possible but I
personally have not heard any such thing
that any such thing happened that the
Rafal became useless in this war with
Pakistan. I've heard no such things and
I am in touch with various people and
I've not heard that. So listen let's not
give too much credence to rumors. Uh one
way to understand whether this is true
or not, whether these such rumors are
possibly true or not is to wait and
watch and see how is the interaction and
the relationship going forward between
the governments of India and France. Is
there any friction that's visible? If
there is friction that visible, if there
is some tension that's visible, then
maybe there could possibly
perhaps be perhaps
some potential hypothetical truth to
this uh to this scenario. Yeah. So
that's one way of finding out but I
personally have heard no such thing. So
I'm pretty sure it's still a very good
aircraft for
us. Uh the great revolution says how
would Chanak take control of India?
Modern India if Chanaki was alive today
how would it take control of India?
That's a very naughty scenario to ask
because that that involves regime
change. What did Chanake do in about 2
and a half thousand years ago? He
conducted an internal coup in India, a
regime change
operation. He fought against the
government of India. The government of
India was the Nanda Empire based out of
Partipra. Right? I'm sure the Nanda
Empire was not very good and not very
good for the people of India. So that
gives you the moral authority to fight
against the government.
So at that time the government of India
was based out of Patutra not Dhi and the
government of India was the government
of the Nanda Empire. So Chanaka what he
did is that he found a sharp brilliant
young boy and we don't know the boy's
parentage. He was definitely not a noble
of noble blood. This boy this guy was
Chandra Gupta and we don't know why he's
called Moria. Maybe because his mother's
name was Mora or maybe he was from a
place called Mora or something. But
yeah, Chandra Gupta was the boy. So, so
Vishnu Gupta Chanaka identified this
brilliant young boy. He trained him,
promoted him, taught him everything and
then somehow or the other they they uh
executed a very effective regime change
operation that involved military
campaigns and fighting against the
government and the Indian armed forces
of that time militarily overthrowing the
government and placing Chandra Gupta
Moria as the new emperor of India.
That's what he did. It was not a civil
war situation because civilians were not
involved. It was a regime change
operation and it was an overthrow of the
then government of
India. So that's what he did then. How
would he do it today? Well, I will leave
it to your imagination because I don't
want to discuss such things over here
which involves overthrowing the the
existing government and internal regime
operation. See the thing is when there
is a regime change it's it's a very
destabilized time for an whenever you
the there's a nation that under goes a
regime change for good reasons or bad
reasons there's a period of chaos
there's a period of great uncertainty
and at such times if you have dangerous
neighbors they will certainly definitely
100% they will take advantage of the
situation by grabbing your territory and
by doing atrocities on your people and
so on. Now we are in that situation
today that if there is chaos in the
country the Chinese and the Pakistanis
will take advantage the Bangladeshes
will take advantage even the Maldis will
want to take advantage imagine that
everybody will will try and take
advantage everybody will try and take
bites out of Indian territory right so
in today's day and age you don't want
that sort of chaotic situation you don't
want that sort of uh situation where
there is uh chaos in the country and and
instability in a country even for just a
couple of years. You don't want that. So
it's not a good idea at this time,
right? Okay. Spade says SAR are India
and Rossia. Rossia. Yes. Is India and
Russia aligned on Bangladesh issue? So
UNOS is pro America. The army general is
said said to f favor Russia and India.
He visited Russia last year. Is UNUS
delaying pools for a US base on that
island?
Eunos is a mercenary. Okay. He's he
spent his life serving foreign masters.
That's why as as as reward he was given
this this bone, this Nobel Peace Prize.
You know who else got the Nobel Peace
Prize? Kissinger. Henry Kissinger. You
see this book here? You see that book
there? This white book here. There's a
book over here and some more. Henry
Kissinger. One of the most evil guys who
ever lived. He won a Nobel Peace Prize.
Who else put Nobel Peace Prize? Barack
Obama guy who dropped more bombs on
innocent people than George W. Bush and
so on. So people are given Nobel peace
prizes prizes for as a reward for for
for services rendered. So Ununus is that
and he we know he's involved with Soros
Foundation with with various other
foundations and so on. So he's a classic
puppet. He's a classic Vasal. That's
Ununos. the army generally seems to be
perhaps possibly slightly more sensible.
I'm not sure why one hears that. Um so
he visited Russia last last year and so
on. Um and uh US base on the island. So
I had spoken about the possibility of a
US base on the island like what 2023 or
something around that
time. Um so what is actually happening
are India and Russia aligned on the
Bangladesh issue?
Yunos seems to be also you know wooing
China. He went to China and he he gave a
speech where he said that Bangladesh can
cut off the rest of cut off India's far
east northeast and make it a completely
completely landlocked region. He first
said country landlocked country then
said landlocked region that sort of
thing. So he is a very problematic
person and he would love to serve
anybody as long as it hurts India. if
the US is no longer interested, he will
certainly serve the Chinese and so on.
Um, and Eunus, his government is an
illicit government. It's an illegitimate
government. It's an
undemocratically placed in power
government. They haven't come to power
through elections. They came through
power came to power through a coup, a
regime change operation.
Um so I'm not sure what the deal is
where when there will be elections and
all that and if elections happen will
there be they these elections be
legitimate elections because if they're
overseen by Eunus and his cronies there
these are not legitimate elections
uh and so on. But the real question
you're asking is are India and Russia
aligned on the Bangladesh issue? I'm not
sure about that right now. What is
Russia's perspective on Bangladesh? If
China and Bangladesh are aligned then
maybe the Russians will want to not
displease China by not interfering too
much and so on. So I think it it still
remains to be seen. I have not been
paying too much attention to the
Bangladesh issue right now because of
other things that have been happening.
So maybe I need to take a look at this
and and see exactly where everybody
stands. Where does Israel stand visa
with Bangladesh? Where does the the US
actually stand right now after things
have changed with Bangladesh? Is
Bangladesh more inclined towards China
right now or is it actually going in the
direction of Russia? And what's the
relationship between Bangladesh army and
India? What is the deal between
Bangladesh and other subcontinental
nations especially Pakistan? What about
Nepal? What about Maldives? I need to
and what about Myanmar? That's an
interesting thing. So I think I need to
revisit this entire matter and maybe we
can discuss this in the next episode.
I'm not 100% sure where Russia stands
with Bangladesh right
now. Okay. Zishan says, "How can India
ever reach the level of the US or China
if it suffers from permanent
disadvantages like being surrounded by
enemies and a religiously divided
population?" Love your work from
Washington DC. Thank you so much Zishan
G. Thank you so
much. Yeah. You know what? A nation that
is too
diverse, it's it's hard for the nation
to succeed. I mean, the US is a pretty
homogeneous nation in a certain way.
Look, it's it's it's a multicultural
multi-thnic nation. You've got the
majority white population, which is
which will soon become a minority
population. You have a lot of African
origin people. You have a lot of what
you call Hispanic people. You have a
small population that has some uh native
ancestry. And then you have people from
other parts of the world like China,
India and so on so forth. A very diverse
population. And yet this nation is
essentially an autocracy that
masquerades as a democracy. And when you
are an autocracy, a uni party system,
then you can control everybody, right?
And you can keep things very much under
control and it doesn't matter who the
president is as long as the president
doesn't doesn't come in the way of the
of the big agenda. So that's how the US
runs. So the US and and the Chinese have
sought to emulate the US. The Chinese
actually idolize the US. The Chinese
hero worshiped the US even though the
two are adversaries today. And the
Chinese have sought to emulate
everything the Americans have done. And
this they started the program of
emulating the US in the
1980s. So uh that's how China has
reached where it is by learning a lot
from the eventual adversary. They knew
the US was their adversary from day one.
The Americans took a long time to catch
up with that situation. So the Chinese
are also a uni party system. A uni and
they are not just a uni party system.
They are a very homogeneous
population. Or are they? The Chinese
also have lots of ethnic groups who are
nonhanchinese. Right? You have the
people of Yunan who are not Chinese who
are not Hanchinese. The people of Yunan
are Thai people. Thai or th ai/ dai.
Thai. Who are these people? They're the
same ethnicity as the people of Thailand
and the same ethnicity as the people of
the ancestors of the Oh people of of
India. Right? So the people of Yunan are
Thai. They are under under Chinese
occupation. The people of Tibet are of
Tibetan ethnicity. They are under
Chinese occupation. The people of Inner
Mongolia are of Mongolian ethnicity, not
Chinese and so on. The people of
Shinjang are of Turk ethnicity. The
people of Manchua are of Manchu
ethnicity, not Hanchinese and so much
more. So China is also kind of like the
US ethnically diverse but China has
imposed the monoculture on its country
one language one culture one system and
they have impose it by force through
brutality through brutality. So these
are both
autocracies and you have a tremendous
amount of advantage if you are an
autocracy because you can get things
done because you don't tolerate
disscent. In the US they don't really
tolerate descent. There will allow
so-called free speech and blah blah blah
but the moment you genuinely go against
the interests of the
establishment it won't end up it won't
end well for you. You see that over and
over again in the US. It's very easy for
you to get shot shot by cops in the US.
Okay. Very easy for somebody to get shot
by cops, to get shot by robbers, to get
killed by a by by by by what's the thing
they have invented? Uh serial killers.
The US invented serial killers, right?
Every town, city, village has either
vampires or serial serial killers and so
on. So in the US, you're allowed to have
so-called free speech, but the moment
you your actions go against the
interests of the establishment, you're
done. And the same goes for China. So
very similar nations in the case of
India very different very different we
have permanent disadvantages like Zishan
is rightfully pointing out we are
surrounded by
enemies right and we have a population
that's divided in so many different ways
religious divide there's the linguistic
divide and there's god knows what other
divides you know then now we have
invented cast divides we have invented I
don't know what other divides we have
India is a nation that that keeps on
creating more problems for itself and a
nation that does this has no realistic
chance of surpassing the US or China. So
this this needs to change. We have too
much democracy like the Chinese keep on
pointing out. They keep on pointing out
India as an example of a nation that has
too much democracy. Not the US. They
won't point out the US because the US is
not really a democracy. Two party system
one step above a one party system and
both parties have the same policy
essentially. So the US is a monoparty
uni uni party system. India is a true
democracy a chaotic democracy and uh
it's not good for India. Most of India's
energy and vitality goes in fighting
itself. Internal friction internal um
yeah friction resistance you know when
you have a current that passes through
wire there's certain amount of
resistance. If you have a superconductor
there's zero resistance you in the case
of India we are not a superconductor. We
are not a regular conductor. We are a
very bad conductor of electricity. So we
have a tremendous amount of friction and
resistance from within. Our entire
energy is it's spent fighting ourselves
among ourselves arguing and shouting and
fighting and talking and having
elections every other week. That's where
all the energy goes. So something needs
to change otherwise India will never
catch up. So Zean points out what he
points out is is very true. Something
needs to change. very deep reforms in
the country otherwise we not going to
end up going
anywhere senpai says when a Pakistan
fragments how can India strengthen its
influence in the new
states okay should India establish
military bases like the US and Japan and
South Korea or focus on investments
trade etc instead when frag Pakistan
fragments so Pakistan will fragment
maybe in the next 3 months maybe next
three years maybe most at most next 20
years. So when that happens, what does
India do? How do we strengthen our
influence in the new
states? Establishing military bases or
like the Americans in Japan, South
Korea, etc. Focus on investments, trade,
etc. What we should do, we should have a
multi-pronged approach when this
happens. First of all, we should act as
a civilizational
mentor to these newly created nations.
Okay, you are a newly created nation.
You've come out of chaos. You came out
of civil war. You fought the Pakistan
army and you won. But you are
devastated. Your economy is in shambles.
Blah blah blah blah blah. So, we're
going to hold your hand and help you get
up on your feet. We're going to give you
economic aid. We're going to, you know,
help you rebuild your institutions.
We're going to build libraries for you.
We're going to build schools for you.
We're going to build a parliament house
for you. We're going to show you how to
write a constitution. We're going to
show you how to draft laws. If you need
something, you ask us. We're going to
have observers and helpers for you.
That's what we need to do. Then we will
help you with trade. You need trade,
we're going to invest. We will invest.
We will build factories of so and so
things for you. And your people will as
a result get jobs and they will also get
expertise. So we can in we can invest.
we can set up industries over there for
those nations in a nice way without
exploiting them. We can do all those
things. Um so trade is a very good way
of doing it. Cultural exchange is a very
good way of doing it. Uh mentoring a
nation uh by by helping them with
institutional uh with creating
institutions and maintaining
institutions, running institutions. All
those things we can do and we cannot
allow outsiders to come in, step in
after we break up the break up Pakistan
and the US comes in and says okay now we
will take care of things. No, stay out
none of your business. So we have to do
that. So that's how we see what we
should have done in Bangladesh after 71
is we should have helped them set up
their democracy, their government, their
institutions, their education system. We
should have invested in that nation's
economy and set up industries and things
for them. We should have had Indians all
over the place working across Bangladesh
interacting with the people. That's how
you do things. And we we instead of
doing that we just stepped out of of the
of the place and just let it go to the
dogs. So it has to be a multi-pronged
multi-level multi-dimensional approach.
We have to help them in every possible
way without exploiting them like the
west would do. Right? That's what needs
to happen. And then over time we can
slowly examine the possibility of
reintegrating them into India whenever
the time is
right. Yes sir. I know you're watching
CIA Sand S. Thank you so much. I
appreciate the
contribution. Uh, Geopolitical Dubai
asks, "Why is France reluctant to share
the source code?" I think I've I took
that question some time ago. Maybe it's
a repeated question. All right. AJ
Sharma says, "Views on Putin. Will
history be kindered to
him?" You know, Putin brought Russia
back from the abyss, from the brink of
the abyss. Russia was on the brink of
the abyss under Boris Yelen. So
Gorbachev was the guy who broke the
Russian nation, who broke the USSR, who
dismantled everything his predecessors
had worked so hard to build. Of course,
the DK started before him, no question
about it. But he could have done
something about it on the instead of
doing that, he allowed the nation to
disintegrate and he then appeared in
pizza commercials for the US. So it
would not be wrong for the people of
Russia to regard Gorbachov as a traitor,
a western
stoogge, a western agent, an agent not
of the British like we say over here in
India but agent an agent of the US. Then
the
Americans they they invested let's say
in Yelen. So Yelson was their guy
drunk. He appeared drunk in public at
times and a guy who was least interested
in anything. He let the Russian economy
go to the dogs. Very soon after he comes
to power, the Russian economy is in
shambles. People are lining up for soup
and bread. And the USSR had a
collectivized economy,
right? Which means that everything in
the USSR, the whole economy was the
collective property of the people. every
single ruble that the people of the USSR
had saved this life savings where they
exist that existed in the form of the
economy of the USSR. So it was the
savings of generations of Russians. That
was the economy of the US USSR. And
Yelin takes that and he gives it away to
a bunch of people, the so-called
oligarchs. And those oligarchs then
proceed to take these
huge this huge capital huge amount of
capital and these huge industries and
they proceeded to run them into the
ground deliberately.
They proceeded to destroy the economy of
the USSR
deliberately. So that's what Yelin
oversaw. He precided over the deliberate
destruction of the life savings of
generations of
Russians. And then he wanted to open up
the country to the west so that the west
the US can come in and start exploiting
all the incredible mineral and natural
resources and wealth of the USSR of
Russia. by the time there was a
plan and he also messed up in Cheschna
and whatn not okay that's what it did
but then you know he became too unfit to
rule and then power was passed on to a
small un unknown guy who had served in
some bureaucratic positions who was a
former KGB agent uh Vladibir Putin no
one knew Vladibin he was some some
random some low low reasonably low
ranking bureau bureaucratic guy with a
with a intelligence uh track record
past. So everybody thought that he will
be controlled easily but Putin had his
own ideas and uh it took him at least a
decade but he put Russia back on track.
He brought Russia he pulled Russia back
from the brink of the abyss from
complete disintegration and by the 2010s
Russia's military was again feared and
whenever they did those zapad exercises
and was exercises and so on so forth
Europe would would be worried you know
so by the 2010s Russia's war machine was
again in reasonably good shape today
it's very different today Putin has
spent more than 25 years in various
forms of power and I so the question is
how will history look at Vladimir Putin?
How will he be remembered in history?
How will history books speak write about
Putin a 100 years from today? I think it
all depends on the succession. See, Mr.
Putin is in his 70s
now and in a few years it's obvious that
he will have to hand over power to
whoever is going to be his
successor. The most crucial time for an
empire or a kingdom or a nation is the
transition phase from one ruler to
another. If you mess that up, then
you're going to be remembered as a
disaster. You may be the greatest ruler
of all, but if you don't handle the
transition right, if you don't ensure
that after my going the right person is
in power, if you don't ensure that, then
whatever you did was
worthless. Because if you hand over
power to the wrong person, that person
will destroy everything you you worked
so hard for. So it is crucial for Mr.
Putin to handpick the right
successor. If he does that and if the
next person is even 50% as good as him,
then Putin will be remembered as Putin
the
Great. Kavia says, "Did Jesus Christ
really live on the planet? Did the
church create Santa Claus and Jesus to
keep keep kids and adults in check?
You're asking me a very very
controversial question. Did Mr. Jesus
Christ actually
exist? Um, look, we have not found any
actual archaeological evidence of the
existence of Mr. Christ. Um
um but yeah there is so much there's a
whole cult a whole religion that's built
around him and there is this uh this uh
monument this this architectural
um building the church of this holy
sepulkar or something which is rumored
to be the resting place of Mr. Christ
and so on but it has not been
archaeologically proven 100%. There's
the shroud of Turin that was dated
carbon dated to the to the Middle Ages,
but some other kind of testing
apparently claims that it's it goes back
almost 2,000 years. There's all kinds of
ambiguity and controversy about this
from a completely realistic hard
evidence perspective. uh we don't have
hard awareness of his existence but I
would say most likely
somebody most likely he probably must
have existed otherwise so many people
would not
u believe in him is it uh I think the
first mentions of Jesus
Christ they they are from at least 100
years after he's supposed to have lived
which is a big red flag actually
similarly there there are there are
there is a story of Uklid the Greek the
Greek mathematician or something there
is no evidence a person called Uklid
actually
existed you know so there are lots of
such madeup stories I I don't know if I
say Mr. the Christ did not live then
lots of people will get very upset you
know but uh from an evidence perspective
I think it's still
missing but similarly that
way because see if if take for example
Kaneshka the great who lived about 2
almost 2,000 years ago now do we have
evidence he existed we have statues of
him from his time we have his
inscription that he himself had written
in Rabatak in Gandhar now part of
Afghanistan at that time it part of
India the robatak inscription of
kaneshka himself in which he writes his
his who he is and his ancestral lineage
um so when it comes to kaneshka we have
hard evidence of his existence from his
time itself not from 100 200 years after
he died but for when it comes to Mr.
Jesus Christ. I don't think there's an
evidence any hard inscriptional or other
evidence of of his existence from the
time that he is supposed to have lived.
Whatever writings turn up, they are from
at least a 100 years after he supposed
to have died, which is kind of, you
know, from a completely realistic
perspective, it it is kind of a red
flag. Uh but yeah so I think it's it's
still a question mark but it's a it's
part it's a part of a a lot of people's
faith. I think Christianity is probably
the second biggest or something like
that religion in the world. So yeah it
is what it
is. VK18 says how does the future look
utopian or dystopian? You know the world
is somewhere in between. It's never
completely black completely white. It's
somewhere in between. But one way of
looking at this is from my favorite
genre of of of fiction. Since I was a
little kid, the my favorite genre was
science fiction. All I would read is
science fiction. You know, Fred Hy who I
mentioned earlier, he wrote a couple of
science fiction books. Asimov kind of Da
but I did read his books. Very
interesting books. Um Arthur C. Clark,
uh Larry Nan, so many so many writers of
science fiction.
Um, so if you and and I was very
fortunate as a kid to have access to a
library that had a whole stash of
science fiction books from something
called the science fiction book club
London from the 1950s and60s. So as a
kid I I grew up reading science fiction
from the 1950s and60s. And if you read
those stories they are so incredibly
beautiful. They speak about beautiful
future
worlds. Very very optimistic worldview
was there in the 1950s and 60s in
science fiction. Okay. Very optimistic
worldview that humanity will reach the
stars and that sort of thing. You may
have alien invasions or whatever but it
will be a situation in which you are a
very very uh technologically advanced
society that's invaded by aliens and
everyone's happy
essentially. So the future was depicted
as a utopian kind of future. It was a
very it was a very positive outlook
towards the future that you had in the
1950s and60s. Now if you read today's
science fiction it's all
dystopian. So something has changed in
the world from the 1950s to the
2020s in the in the ensuing time period
of of 70 years fiction has become more
and more
dystopian which kind of tells you the
direction in which the world is going
that you know we've had we are seeing so
many advances in technology but who's
controlling the technology and what is
it being used for? Everybody can see
that it's being used to consolidate.
It's been used for the purpose of
consolidating consolidating power in the
hands of of a small number of
people and the rest of the world they
are being used as guinea pigs on
which or or or as resources right so
yeah from that perspective if if the
wrong people get all the power and they
use the technology to amass even more
power then the world will go in a
dystopian will go towards a dystopian
direction even if we reach
Mars, okay? And set up a population
center on Mars. Who's going to control
Mars? It's going to be one person, one
government,
right? And what's the value system of
that one person, one government? Is it
what you need in the world? So, yeah,
the future kind of looks dystopian at
this point in time. It does. And for the
future to change, to become more
utopian, to become better, you need a
multipolar world. You can't have a world
which is controlled by one or two
powers and you especially need a nation
like India to rise and become part of
the multipolar world which is why India
is so important for the world in my
opinion. Okay. Games rich says what's
your opinion on Penrose's twister
theory. Twisters are one step ahead of
even tensors. So look it's it's a
mathematical construct that's used in
string theory and other things. Twister
theory it's used in string theory. It's
also used in general relativity, but
it's not a theory of physics. It's a
it's a mathematical tool that we use in
physics. So, it's not some it's a it's a
good tool to have. You know, string
theory has has given us so many really
interesting mathematical tools to work
with. But at the end of the day, they
are tools. These are invented tools. Are
are they discovered tools? You know, the
question is always there. Lots of
YouTube channels ask this question. Is
mathematics invented or discovered?
Well, mathematics is the language of the
world of the universe. It it simply uh
is a description of the regularities and
patterns in the universe.
But how to solve differential equations?
We invent techniques for solving
differential equations. But differential
equations represent patterns and
regularities in the world. Similarly,
twister theory is is uh well, twisters
are are objects that can describe
physical phenomena and so on and can be
used to solve problems that are part of
various theories. So, it's a useful tool
to
have. Beyond that, I don't have much
opinion about twister theory. It's it's
a nice thing to have like rejipole
theory and so on, you
know. Okay. Lakshi Kana says, "Why did
India decline the opportunity to join
the GCAP program which could have
enhanced its defense capabilities?" What
is GCAP? You have stumped me sir. I'm
stumped by at least three sentiments.
Let me find out what is the GCAP
program. Um let me go through our friend
Google and we shall together find out
what is GCAP. So first of all, excuse
me. Uh let us go here. Okay, let's see
what is
GCAP. GCAP. GCAP
program. What is this? Okay. Global
combat air program. It's a multinational
initiative led by the UK, Japan, and
Italy and Italy to jointly de develop a
sixth generation stealth fighter. You
see the problem here? The UK is
involved and so are Japan and Italy.
Now, Japan is I mean I'm I'm very fond
of Japan. Italy great history. But today
the UK and Japan and Italy are vasals of
the United States in different ways. The
UK is not part of the EU but it is the
US's premier lap
dog number one
closest. Japan has been under US
permanent military operation occupation
since 1945. Italy has been under
permanent US military occupation also
like Japan since 1945. Japan and the UK
and Italy have had their constitutions
essentially written by the by Americans
or under complete under American
supervision. So these are three nations
that are US vasals. They are developing
jointly developing apparently this uh
sixth generation stealth
fighter. You don't want to be part of
that because you're going to get
compromised. you will not not get all
the
technology and even if you get the
fighter plane it may have problematic
uh
characteristics when you need to take it
out for for a combat mission military
mission you may find that at the exact
minute you need its capabilities it will
not do what it's supposed to do and so
on so you know what you have there are
no shortcuts in safe. It's a nice
opportunity. You think that they have
offered us the opportunity, they given
us the opportunity, the invitation to
join this program. It may be a trap for
us. There are no free lunches in the
world. There are no shortcuts in the
world. If you want a sixth generation
fighter plane, you first develop your
own fifth generation fighter plane and
then use the learnings of that to take
to take the next step and develop a
sixth gen generation fighter player. you
the only technology you can trust is
technology you have developed
yourself because if you take somebody
else's developed technology then there
will be issues with that you will not be
in full control so I think India has
done the right thing I know it it it
feels like we are giving up we are you
know passing passing on good
opportunities but it's not the case it's
the right thing to
do okay
uh Akar says eam's book the India
reveals China's lust for deception,
deceiving the heavens to cross the ocean
or making a sound in the east and strike
west. How to assertain the truth
especially with respect to China's
economy. Uh I may have that book
somewhere here but I haven't read it. So
okay the India way right he I think Dr.
Jashankar has has authored at least two
books in the past few years if I'm not
mistaken. So the Chinese like this is
nothing new about China. Read Sunsu. His
book is full of aphorisms like these,
strategys like this. Uh yeah, deceiving
the heavens to cross the ocean and blah
blah blah. Oh, this this is very
Sununzuish stuff. The Chinese have
always been like this. You know what?
Everybody is like this. Every power that
make that actually matters follows these
rules and principles. The Chinese are
not special. They're not superior to the
rest of the world because they have nice
little aphorisms and nice little
strategys in a small book. The Chinese
have always been like this. But for us
we we have given we have settled
ourselves with this with this belief
that Chinese are super inscrutable super
um
um advanced in in these practices and
whatn not okay they are every nation
wants to deceive the rest of the world
as per when it comes to its capabilities
it's only Indians to to an extent that
want to advertise you know we have done
this we've done that no keep quiet mind
your business and let the world believe
what it wants while we rise. That's how
it should be. Uh so how to assert in the
truth especially with respect to China's
economy? We have to first of
all be clear about one fact. The Chinese
will not reveal everything about their
economy and whatever they will claim
will most likely be an exaggeration. It
doesn't mean that we should
underestimate the Chinese economy. So
let's say they are saying that we are
growing. Let's say hypothetically the
Chinese claim this year hypothetically
that we are growing at 6% a year. Maybe
they are growing at 4% a year. Maybe. So
you have to take their claims with a
grain of salt. But it is stupid to
believe that because instead of 6% they
are growing at 4% that means that they
are weak. They're not weak. They've done
a tremendous amount of hard work the
past 30 40 years. Don't underestimate
them. So it's difficult to know what's
actually happening inside China because
the system is so opaque. Right? They
hide the truth from the world because
they want to hide their weaknesses and
they want to claim something more than
what they are. But it is still stupid to
underestimate them. So the truth
somewhere usually lies somewhere in
between between this and that between
two polar opposite
ends. So you should we should understand
we should we should uh be clear about
one thing. We will never know know
exactly what's happening within China
whether it's from the economic
perspective from the political
perspective from uh a military
perspective we will not ever be able to
know exactly what's happening in China
unless we have ways of hacking into the
systems and all that and if we have such
ways and means we will not talk about
them right so for us in the public it's
very hard to assert in the truth we
should know that the truth is
somewhere it's not what China is
claiming but the Chinese uh are not to
be underestimated. That's what I would
say. Harsh says, "Thoughts on polygamy?
What's its pros and cons? If you're
capable, can you do it or not?" Look, in
our culture, there is no we don't have
any any procriptions, any prohibitions
on polygamy or even
polyandry, right? We we never have these
things. I don't know why we have these
laws today that you can't do this or
that. Let people decide what whatever
the hell they want. For most people it's
it's it makes no sense to have polygamy
or polyandry. Makes no sense. But if
some people want to do it, let them do
it. I I would say leave it to the
people. Don't don't let the law decide.
In Indian culture, we never had this
prohibition on polygamy. It doesn't mean
that I'm pro polygamy or anti polyolyam.
I'm just saying we never had any
prohibition. And generally, most people
can't even afford to have multiple
spouses, right? I mean, come on. How how
do you do that? So it it just makes
sense for one person to have one one
spouse only because you know the human
population is generally 50/50 male and
female. So I think it's a very unusual
situation where where polygamy would be
practiced. In India it was generally
kings who would practice polygamy or
maybe very rich people who would
practice polygamy. Most people simply
could not afford it. Uh so that's a
strictly
nonmoralizing perspective that I'm
giving you. What are the pros and cons?
I think you can decide for
yourself. General Vladimir Put says, "If
we travel 20,000 light years via
wormhole, faster than light, can we see
the Earth's past using an advanced
telescope catching that ancient light?"
That's a thought experiment you're
proposing, sir. I don't think we can see
the Earth's past using an advanced
telescope uh catching that ancient
light. Look, uh, traveling 20,000 light
years via a
wormhole doesn't mean you're traveling
faster than light. It means that you are
using a shortcut in the shortcut in the
fabric of spaceime. And the good old
cliche is you take a piece of paper and
you poke a hole through it and bend it
like that. And that that you know if you
had traveled in a straight line, it
would have taken you such a long
distance. But because you have bent
spacetime itself, you're able to travel
very fast. So it means that you have
traveled from point A to point B faster
than it would have taken you to travel
regularly. So it looks like it's super
lumininal travel but it's
not. So by doing that you don't actually
end up uh traveling through time. Okay.
But there are ways of traveling through
time that are not prohibited via
Einstein's equations of general
relativity. And there are thought
experiments you can actually do in which
you know um time dilation becomes a
factor and so on so forth. But whatever
you do you won't be able to
um see earth's past. I think it's very
difficult for me to imagine a scenario
in which you you can see the earth's
past. So I think um look I'm not going
to sit down and do the calculations
right now and look at this particular
thought experiment. It's an interesting
thought experiment you proposed here. Um
it's something that can be given as an
exercise to a high school or college
student you know to figure out whether
if you travel to a place that's 20,000
lighty years away through a shortcut
which is an Einstein Rosen bridge also
known as wormhole then will you be able
to see the earth's
past will you be able to see it so or
let me do it right now so let's say I am
at a place that's 20,000 light years
away right now and I'm looking at the
earth through telescope I will obviously
see something that happened 20,000 years
ago now now if I reach there right now
and I look at the earth I'll actually be
looking back in
time yeah you're right so yes I did the
thought experiment in my mind now so if
you travel 20 years 20,000 light years
away by a wormhole why some kind of
shortcut which seems like faster than
light but it's not then if you look at
the earth you will through the
past. True. Very good. Good job. Yes,
you will through the
past. All right. Rishi says, um, Aim
Munir has been promoted to five-star
rank. Why do you think the step was
taken considering the fact that the
Pakistan army already has overwhelming
power inside Pakistan? It's just to
consolidate the legitimacy of the
Pakistani army. They have put out this
fiction that they have done very well,
performed very well in this three-day
war against India. we have brought down
85 Indian fighter planes and 200 Indian
UFOs and we have shot down we we have
destroyed 28 Indian air bases or
something like that that sort of claim
they have made
right so if you make that claim then you
have to give some reward to your general
otherwise it looks like you're lying so
to make the story seem true you have to
actually give rewards and promotions to
your armed forces personnel that's why
they have done it to to keep up
appearances and to mislead the people of
Pakistan that you know this actually
happened that's why we are promoting the
great aim who brought us this glory
against
India okay Karthik Gandhi says why do
you include Israel in the sovereign
country
list yeah I I all these all I mean the
past year or so when I spoke about the
sovereign countries I said there are
four sovereign nations US the US, China,
Russia and India apart from that I said
there are no other sovereign sovereign
nations but After rethinking my thought
process and so on and taking a fresh
look at the world, I have realized
Israel is a fully sovereign nation. Now
the question is why do I include Israel
now is as in in the list of sovereign
nations, five sovereign nations.
Well, when you have the when you have a
nation like the US that prioritizes
Israel's national interest and will
never do a thing that will hurt Israel's
national interests and the US happens to
be the most powerful nation nation in
the world then you can at least say that
Israel is a fully sovereign nation right
if it has such incredible
influence influence I'm saying I'm not
saying power I'm just saying influence
but if it has so much influence in the
over the US maybe it is a fully
sovereign nation just from that
perspective I think you
tell that that Israel is a fully
sovereign nation. Akar says, "What's the
probability that the Starlink
constellation of thousands of satellites
contains infrared senses sensors to to
detect to early detect the launch of
intercontinental ballistic missiles? I
think there's a very high close to 100%
probability that the Starling
constellation of satellites doubles as a
surveillance network.
Okay, I'm sure they have remote sensing
capabilities and they can see what's
happening all across the world in real
time. To what resolution can they see? I
don't know. Do they have infrared
sensors? I don't know. Do they have
other band sensors? I don't know. But I
am sure they have advanced surveillance
capabilities. Can they can some of these
satellites detect the launch of an ICBM?
I'm pretty sure some of them at least
will have it. Will all of them have it?
I'm not sure about that.
Um but yeah I think it's a surveillance
mechanism. Can I show comments on the
stage? Can
I maybe I can maybe I can't. Okay. So
yeah. So so that's the answer. It's
definitely a surveillance
um network. Okay. Now
next next is by project smiling Buddha.
Why do Indian students coming abroad
lack
confidence? Um why do Indians overall
lack confidence? Because of the
education system and the media and all
that. Because of the uh of the mentally
colonized people around them. It's it's
a self-fulfilling prophecy kind of
thing. It's a self-sustaining um
environment. See the education system. I
had a a question from some time from I
think the first question I took today
was why did India never develop as as a
technological power as an industrial
power. The truth is we had developed
right we were the first fully
industrialized society. We were the
first fully industrialized civilization
fully industrialized and fully urbanized
civilization on the surface of the
planet. But nobody knows this. We don't
teach this to our students in the
education system. We were we accounted
for at least onethird of the entire
world's GDP for most of recorded
history. Do our teachers teach us teach
us this? Do our textbooks teach us this?
When you are not
taught anything about what you have,
what your ancestors accomplished, then
you will end up believing grow up
believing that you come from a
civilization of
losers and you will feel that everybody
else is superior to you because they did
all these things. We did nothing. So you
will automatically see everybody who has
a different appearance from foreign
foreign nation as being superior to you.
That's the inferiority complex. Then the
Indian
media it reinforces these stereotypes.
The Indian entertainment system
reinforces these stereotypes. So
everybody and and your and everybody
around you the elders they also have
grown up believing this. So they also
will reinforce the stereotypes. So it's
a self reinforcing system that we have
in India that we are a nation of losers.
We never achieved anything. We never had
a sense of history. We never wrote
books. We only memorized things. We had
no education system. We are a backward
culture blah blah blah blah blah over
and over again that's why Indians lack
confidence Indians have this crushing
sense of inferiority because of all
these things so that there's your answer
sir Bharava says I consider corruption
to be the biggest hindrance to India's
development do you see the ethos of
Indians changing discipline and honesty
increasing among Indians I could not
agree more with Mr.
Bharav corruption is India's number one
pro problem
today what India needs is a war against
corruption the moment you cut down even
50% of India's corruption half the
problems in the country will disappear
why do we have a 100 million possibly
Bangladeshes in India because of
corruption why do we have lacks of
cookies and lacks of Rohingyas and god
knows how many Pakistanis in India
because of corruption why our are our
borders borders so poorest because of
corruption. Most of the problems in
India exist because of corruption. If
you remove corruption, the education
systems quality will
increased drastically. If you remove
corruption, the the the painful process
of of interfacing with the government
that most Indians have to face, it will
disappear. Mr. Bharav is so right.
India's number one problem is corruption
and which politician from top to bottom
do you see talking about this where is
India's war on
corruption and you know we are made to
believe that corruption is our fault
because we are a corrupt society that's
why we have corruption I'll tell you why
corruption exists Indians are not a
corrupt people we have no we have never
been a corrupt society you know who
introduced corruption into India it's
the British how did they introduce
corrupt caption into India. They created
the Indian administrative services,
Indian civil services they were called
and other institutions of India, the
legal institution, other institutions,
right? And the objective of creating
these institutions was to create the
infrastructure of occupation over India
and of control over India. So the armed
forces, the British armed forces were
created, British Indian armed forces,
the British Indian police system which
continues today, the British
administrative system which continues
today in India, the education system
which continues in India. All of these
institutions that created had a certain
purpose of enslaving Indians. And if
they had a judicial system, that
judicial system was meant was created
for the purpose of serving the
British. When Indians would approach the
judicial system, they were made to go
through a different process. They had to
pay bribes. If a British
person, you know, went to the judicial
system in India during British
occupation, they would never have to pay
a bribe. But if you were Indian and you
had to approach the law, you had to pay
bribes at every stage of the way, at
every step of the process, and you had
to pay bribes to Indians because Indians
were made to oppress Indians. Whether it
was the bureaucracy, whether it was the
judiciary of the British, whether it was
whatever
else institution, the the system of the
the process of corruption was
institutionalized as an additional
measure of oppressing Indians. And the
system the British created continued
intact after 1947, which is why
corruption continued intact in India.
And it became even more deported and
entrenched after
1947. That's what happened. We are not a
corrupt people. The system is such that
the only way to deal with a lot of the
government machinery is through
corruption. We have no
choice. The people of India have no
choice. So most people will will just
give in. Okay, let's pay a bribe and get
it done. So that's why Indians are so
cynical because you know that's the way
the system works. It's not the fault of
the Indians. It is not. And why is there
in discipline in
India? The same Indians who when they go
to a foreign country are the most
disciplined in the world. In India
they're not disciplined. Why is that?
Because they know that there's no point
being being disciplined. Let's say I
want to put trash in a trash can.
H they said that Indians litter on the
roads, right? the Indians litter on the
roads. Let's say first of all you will
not find trash cans in most parts of
India. H but let's say you have trash
cans. So let's say we put the garbage in
trash cans. My question is what happens
after
that? What does the municipality do with
that trash? The trash that you so
assiduously put in the trash can they
will dump it in the ocean or in the
river or in some garbage heap somewhere.
They will not process it. they will not
recycle it. So what's the point of you
putting the trash in the trash can?
Eventually people just get sick and
tired of it and they they just stop
being disciplined. And when this happens
for 70 80 years the whole of the country
becomes like
this. Indians are the most honest people
in the world. They are the by by by
culture by civilization we are the least
corrupt people in the world.
But it is this foreign system that has
ruined the
country and it is high time our leaders
do something about this otherwise they
are
complicit. Anuja says prime minister and
defense minister recently said that we
are only at a pause. Can this pause be a
strategy to have a surprise attack on
Pakistan in a few days? I think we will
have to wait and watch. Uh maybe it is,
maybe it's not. We'll have to see. Um
this is a question of war. So it it it's
it's uh yeah so in in war everything
goes every strategy every method is
acceptable and admissible and we shall
wait and watch and we shall see how it
goes. I will not be displeased if we
finish the job we we started a few days
ago.
Yeah. Literary literally office officer
K says how did Israel get away with the
US's liberty? If that was an Indian
ship, we would have been outraged. Yes,
the Israelis took down the US warship uh
USS Liberty back in the day. Which year
was it? Let's find out. Let us do a
Google search and find out. USS
Liberty. What happened exactly? Right.
USS
Liberty. What did I say? ISS. USS. USS
Liberty incident 1967. It was an attack
on a US Navy technical research ship,
spy ship by Israeli Air Force fighter
jets and torpedo boats in 1967 during
the six- day war. This combined air and
sea attack killed 34 crew members,
wounded 171 crew members and severely
damaged the ship. Israel apologized for
the attack and they said that they
thought it was an Egyptian ship and u so
on. Yeah. So the Israelis got away with
this and that's why I said that Israel
is a is a super sovereign nation. They
can do things to the Americans and they
still can get away with it. Why did they
get away with it? Because I because the
Americans u treat Israel as a super
special nation and they won't do a thing
that will harm Israel. Why is that? I
don't know. But it is it is the case. If
it was an Indian ship, it would have
been outrage for sure. If an
Indian attack had happened on the USS
Liberty and if it was Indian aircraft
and Indian torpedo boats that had
attacked the ship, the Americans would
probably have invaded India and and
probably tried to destroy India. But
Israel gets away with it. So it's a
special nation, isn't
it? Sharma says, "What's the history of
Hindi's closeness to Persian?" The
closeness of of Indian languages to
Persian goes back a long long
time. If you look at old Persian, the
language of the Hakshamish Empire of
Persia, a Kirid Empire, if you that
language was almost identical to
Sanskrit, old Persian. And how was that
uniform script deciphered? Let me put
something on the screen. What did the
uniform script look like? So, so our
Persian neighbors, they had something
called the uniform script. Persian
uniform. Okay. So if you look at the
uniform script of the Persian Empire,
this is what it looked like here. Okay.
This was the script. Uh
E all that sort of thing. Sounds
suspicious suspiciously similar, right?
So this was the script and it was
undeciphered for a very long time. Then
I don't remember who it was that
deciphered it but their hypothesis was
that let's imagine that Persian that the
old Persian language is is very similar
to Sanskrit and then let's try and with
that hypothesis try to decipher the
script and using that hypothesis they
were able to accurately decipher the
uniform script and it turns out that the
old Persian language was almost
identical to Sanskrit. So you see the
Persian people they spoke a language
that was almost identical to Sanskrit
and their ancestors were ancient Indians
the ancient capital of Persia that
Alexander the Greek destroyed what was
it called? It was called
Parhuapur. What is Persia? It's a
corruption of Para of the Para people.
The people who wielded the battle axe
the Paru Paru means battle axe in
Sanskrit. And the people who wield the
Pershu were called the Parhua people.
And they gave their name to the lang to
the land Persia. That's a very ancient
connection that we have with the
Persians, the old Persians. Today's
Persians are different. Today's Persia
is different. 50% of Persia's population
is not Persian anymore and so on. Uh and
the Hindi language, it's a mongrel
language. It's a mixed language. It's
it's obviously an ancient it's a
descendant of an ancient April language
which which obviously has its roots in
ancient Sanskrit obviously um and its
vocabulary is most its grammar is mostly
derived from Sanskrit. This it's the the
vocabulary of Hindi has lots of Persian
and Arabic words. Now a lot of the
Persian words of today are also
descendants of Arabic and Turk loan
words but many Persian words are
descendants of old Persian which has
ties to Sanskrit and so on. So that's
the convoluted history. Um and Hindi or
Hindavi was it's a language that
eventually uh emerged out of uh the
Mughal and Turic courts in North India
and it has so many different dialects
which are non Persianized like Aadi like
methyli like whatever else which have
I'm sure less Persian influence and so
on. So because of the Turk occupation of
India and the fact that they used
Persian as the court language that's how
so much of Persian vocabulary became um
you know enshed in the Hindi language
along with words that have Turic origin
and Arabic origin. The word aad is
Arabic. the word
uh for liver. It's the
Turkish word
So many of the words you use
are of foreign have have foreign origin.
Turkish or Arabic. I am okay with
Persian. Persian is one of our languages
essentially for all intents and
purposes. But yeah
um not sure how to read this. My
sirillic is very rusty. Uh but the
question is why can't India use the
tactics of Israel hitting militants
every few months. I think we have just
very recently changed our doctrine right
um that any terror attack is an act of
war against India. I think let's wait
and watch. I think India is going to use
such tactics going forward. We should
and I agree with you that India should
use the tactics that Israel uses hitting
militants in Pakistan every few months
whenever required. Of course, we would
remember that Pakistan is not Palest is
not Gaza. Pakistan is a different kind
of entity. It's not as helpless and weak
as Gaza. U so it's a different scenario
that we have. But I agree that we should
treat Pakistanis the way the Israelis
treat their enemies without mercy
because they are terrorists. What can
you do? Yes. Indian Sultan. Thank you so
much, sir. Thank you. Way says says,
"Thank you, VA. Thank you so much.
Please bomb Pakistan. Well, I can't bomb
Pakistan, but I hope that uh we end the
menace of terrorism once and for all.
It'll be a great service to the whole
world and also to our own
people. Um Nille Shuranjan Shivasu says,
"Many news outlets are telecasting
increasing cases of corona virus in
Delhi and Maharashtra. Should we worry?"
Uh no. Let's get on with our lives. I'm
I'm done with Corona virus. I think I
never want to hear the that word again
corona
virus. I mean all those waves of corona
virus the shutting down of the whole
world of the whole country what was it
called? Oh mic oh micron oh micron
variant and what enough of this
nonsense if these new news outlets are
are are creating a new scare then there
must be some vested interest behind it.
So uh yeah I I don't think we should
worry and I'm sure the government of
India will not shut the country down
even if something actually happens. The
corona virus is weaker than the flu and
it was clearly designed as a bioweapon
by somebody but you know enough of
corona virus
seriously. Hardig says how can we
protect ourselves from China Pakistan
and Bangladesh and especially China's
dirty tricks tactics of proxy wars via
Pakistan and Bangladesh. The only
long-term realistic solution is for us
to become so
powerful that nothing will work against
India. That's the only way. Right now we
are like a lion surrounded by three four
dogs. But what if we become a
Tyrannosaurus
Rex who can eat a
lion in one in one bite? That's what we
have to
become. Okay. Then the dragon will also
look small. the Chinese dragon and
Pakistan, Bangladesh and whatever else
will be of no no importance anymore.
That's the only long-term solution. In
the meanwhile, we have to be super
vigilant and we have to hit the
terrorists where they exist. We can't
wait for them to come and hit us and
then we hit them back at the border. No,
we have to find them where they are and
hunt them down and eliminate them and
everybody who shelters them and this has
to be an ongoing process. Now, that's
what we have to do. So, we have already
changed our doctrine. We will no longer
wait to be hit. We'll hit whenever
required. And but the only long-term
solution is for us to become huge,
gigantic, keep growing, keep brewing,
become a Tyrannosaurus Rex, a T-Rex, not
a lion, a T-Rex. That's what we need to
do. Animeish says, uh, would you be
making a dedicated video on how to raise
its standards? Uh, maybe I should, but
maybe it's not something that can be
covered in one video. Maybe it should be
a series, but then yeah, I'll have to
think about it. I had actually intended
to do that. It's not happened thus far,
but something else is coming up. So
yeah, really now says Agnikol tested an
electrical semicryogenic engine skyro
with young blood should be funded by
Adani etc to have hundreds of launches
and geoloink. Well, well, I'm glad we
have Agnik, Skyroot, all these all these
startups that are doing really good work
in India. Some of them have fully 3D
printed components on their rockets. Uh,
we need these companies to become the
next, you know, what what Space X's and
and whatnot, right? And u they should be
funded by whoever can fund them. Um it
would be fantastic if we have our own
space
ecosystem public private partnerships.
We have ISRO that's the government
entity which is superb which has some of
the best quality in the world and also
all these up and cominging startups that
can all combine come come together to
create a self- sustaining
ecosystem and it would be so nice to
have something like you know um our own
constellation of satellites just like
Starlink but a better constellation a
better alternative a cheaper alternative
more e efficient effective alternative
which also serves a geopolitical purpose
for us. It would be so great to have
that. So I agree with really now I
do really now says I wish you open a
university for all for all ages. Maybe I
will in the future let's see but uh
thank you for the
suggestion. No idea says why
generalizing India is easy but not the
west. Well it depends on who is doing
it. U the west likes to infantilize
nations portray them as an infantile
society and they try they like to
generalize everything. Give let me give
you a different example.
Africa when you see a black person you
see a
person a person from the perspective of
a western person you see it from western
eyes. When you encounter a person who is
black black ethnicity you see that from
a western perspective. Oh this is
African. You know how big Africa is.
It's like saying when you see a white
person oh this is a white guy or a
European guy. You know in Europe you
have so many different countries and
ethnicities and cultures. You have
Slovenia, you you you you have uh within
France you have so many ethnic groups
actually but it's been homog
homogenized. You have the Slovaks, you
have the Polish people, you have the
Hungarians, they are so different from
each other. A Romanian and a British
person have almost nothing in common but
from from an outside perspective they
look the same. Right now imagine Africa
which is so much larger than Europe has
so many different languages and ethnic
groups who have nothing in common with
each other but from us from from an
outsers's perspective they for us
they're all the same oh African it's a
it's it's so silly
right so this we see it that way because
we have internalized the western
perspective and the west likes to
generalize
um make make generalizations about about
various cultures and all that especially
those they don't like. So and and
they've done that about India also lots
of generalizations and stereotypes
they've created about India
u and they have studied I mean all the
literature that you find about the west
is is very detailed right and very
nuanced but the same authors when they
treat do a treatment literary treatment
or or or academic treatment of other
nations will resort to generalizations
it's it's a it's a case study of double
standards. So it's because they do it
and and because we accept their
perspectives that's why we we feel that
we are being victimized and and
generalized. We need to have our own
scholars who write about the
west and I'm not saying we should make
generalizations. We should have our own
approach and our own academic
treatment really now is says what is the
leverage that Israel has in the deep
state. Well, if I knew that, then I
would Yeah. See, that's that's a big
question. That's that's the trillion
dollar question. I'm not sure what it
is, but they clearly have some
leverage. So, I'm not sure who who is in
the in the right position to answer this
question, but clearly Israel has some
kind of very very deep leverage. I'm not
sure what it
is. Um, PB says, "Please throw some
light on the French Vikings occupying
Britain.
Did the French rule the UK for centuries
and what's the origin of present day
royalty? Um, that's an interesting
question. French Vikings occupying
Britain. It's a very interesting story.
So, what happens is this. You had a
kingdom of France, France, Franka, the
Frankish kingdom where the people were
the Frankish people, the Franks, and
they had their own kings and all that.
One of their kings was Karonus Magnus
also known as
Shaklammana and so on. Now
about,200 or so years ago before today
around the year around the 700s and 800s
the 8th 9th centuries around that time
the people of the Scandinavian region
they started raiding Europe. So let's go
to the map. Where's where where is map?
Let me put uh the map on the screen so
that we uh get some sense of perspective
and direction. So here we have um the
region that we are talking about the
Scandinavian region is Norway, Sweden,
Denmark. That's that's essentially the
Scandinavian countries and later on
Iceland became part of that region of
the Scandinavian ethnic groups uh lands
that they lived in. So around 700 800s
ADs around the time the Scandinavians
also known as the Vikings today they
started uh doing these these seabboard
raids on mainly England mainly what's
today the United Kingdom. Okay. Um and
the first one of the first places they
did a raid at was let me find the place.
Where is it? I've got to find the place.
It's obviously going to be somewhere
over here south of
Edinburgh. Lindesfarn Holy Island and
there's a ruined abbey over here. So,
let's zoom in, zoom in, zoom in. Here we
have it. Now, where's the abbey?
Lindesfarn Abby. There's a ruined abbey,
which is a religious thing. So, this
island is called Holy
Island. And yeah, this has to be the
place somewhere here.
Mindisfarn Abbey. There are ruins all
over the place here. Maybe this is the
one. You can see there's some structure.
There's a ruined castle over
here and so on. So I not bore you with
the details, but this is one of the
first places where the Vikings launched
a raid. It's called
Lindesfarn and so on. So the Vikings
were not just uh raiding England, they
were also raiding France. Okay. Now the
French king eventually proposed a deal
to one of the Viking chieftains. The
name of this Viking chieftain was Rolo.
Rolo. So the French king told Rolo that
you know what? Instead of raiding us all
the time, why don't you settle down in
France? I will give you and your men a
large territory in the western part of
France where you like to raid so much. I
will give you the territory. I will make
you a duke which is the second highest
title after king of France. I will make
you the duke of this place and you
settle down with your men. Here are the
conditions. First
condition, you adopt Christianity. You
give up your pagan mult polytheistic
culture. You become Christianity. That's
the first condition. Second condition,
you will adopt the French language, the
French customs and you will marry French
women. And third condition, you defend
France from the other Vikings.
So this was an offer Rolo could not
refuse. So Rolo became the first duke of
this region which came to be known as
Normandy Normandy. What does Normandy
mean? The realm of the
northmen, the Vikings. So then so Raw
became the first Duke of Normandy. His
son was the second Duke of Normandy. His
grandson was the third Duke of Normandy.
And I think it was around the time of
his great great grandson that there was
an issue. So one of his descendants I
think it was the great great grandson or
some around that time that guy he had to
go he by the time his descendants had
become completely French Norman Normans
but French. So this descendant of Rolo
who was probably the fifth or something
Duke of Normandy he had to go fight a
holy war the
crusades which was fine but he he had a
big problem. He did not have any
legitimate sons.
He had illegitimate sons but he did not
have any legitimate son who he could
make the temporary duke while he was
gone because what if he dies during the
crusades and his son has to take over
right but he had no legitimate sons. So
against his wishes he was forced to give
the title of Duke of Normandy acting
Duke of Normandy to one of his
illegitimate
sons. So this illegitimate son becomes
the next Duke of Normandy and the Duke
of Normandy goes on the crusade and he
dies. So an illegitimate boy becomes the
I think the sixth Duke of Normandy. His
name was Guom or William. And he had a
very rough childhood because everybody
was upset that this illegitimate boy
becomes Duke of Normandy. And there were
many attempts on his life by his
relatives who wanted to take over the
the the the title of Duke and so on. But
he survived and he became a very
powerful duke, the most powerful Duke of
all time, William. And he called himself
William the Bastard because he was
illegitimate, right? And it was in his
in his 50s when he was in his 50s that
he what he did was
this. He built a big
navy and he crossed the English Channel
and he invaded England. absolutely crazy
thing to do, right? By William the
Bastard, Duke of Normandy. And
unfortunately for the king of England,
Harold, just one week before William
lands uh over here some at Hastings.
William lands at Hastings. One week
before that there was another Harold
Harold Hadra who was a Viking king who
had landed in the north of England with
the brother of King Harold
uh Tostig. So Harold, king of England,
had to go all the way north, fight the
Vikings in a horrifying battle, battle
of Stamford Bridge in which he defeated
the Vikings and killed the king and his
army is exhausted and the moment the
battle is over, they hear they get word
that the Normans have landed in the
south of England. So they have to come
rushing all the way south despite being
bruised and battered and then they
engage William the Bastard at Hastings,
the Battle of Hastings. And the battle
is going well, but a stray arrow
catches king of England Harold in his
eye. He dies and William the bastard
becomes William the Conqueror.
So William the Conqueror that is the
origin
story and this happened in the year 1066
AD and from that time the
Saxons you know they lost control of
England and the Normans started ruling
England and the spoke they spoke French
and since the year 1066 AD every single
king or creed of England has been a
descendant of William the Conqueror.
Even the present king of England is a
descendant of William the Conqueror. So
yes, that is the legacy of Rolo the
white king whose descendant William went
from being the bastard to the conqueror.
And for centuries French, Norman French
was the language of the court in in
England and eventually it became part of
common English. That's the story. Very
interesting story. Geopolitical Dubet.
Thank you so much sir. I really
appreciate that. Sergeant Skylan says uh
which is better Tamil Nanu economic
model or the Gujarat economic model
which would be
better I think I'm not sure what the
differences are uh I know Gujarat did
very well under Mr. Modi when he was
chief minister and Gujat probably is the
state with one probably some of the
highest quality living standards in
India very good quality of life and so
on etc. Tamil ladu I'm not sure I'm sure
I've heard that their their economy is
also doing well so I'm sure both these
economic models have some strengths
right and obviously every economic model
will have some drawbacks or deficiencies
I'm not saying what these are because
I'm not examined in detail I would say
we need to take the best of both
approaches and fuse it together right
that's what we should
do Venom says do Monty Hall problems
makes makes sense I'm not sure what the
Monty Hall problem is I'm going to do a
Google search once again. What is the
Monty Hall problem? Let me see. Where is
Google? Monty Hall problem. What is it?
Maybe I know, maybe I don't know, but I
don't remember.
Monty Hall problem. What is that? Is a
brain
teaser in the form of a probability
puzzle based nominally on the American
show Make a
Deal. Okay. Okay. Okay. Suppose you're
in a Gabe show and you're given the
choice of three doors. Behind one door
is a car. Behind the other doors are
goats. You pick a door, say number one,
and the host who knows behind who knows
what's behind the doors opens another
door, say number three, which is a goat.
Then he says to you, do you want to pick
door number two? Is it to your advantage
to switch your
choice? And I believe the answer should
be that you should switch your choice. I
remember reading about this somewhere a
long time ago that it is advantageous to
switch but I don't remember the logic
anymore. So I won't be able to answer
you right now because it will involve
doing a lot of reading but interesting
question you've asked and maybe I should
revisit this. So anyway, thank
you. Uh Viber Chops says do you think
Norththeast insurance will help China
like they did with Pakistan? What's
northeast insurance?
Do you think the northeast insurance
will help China like they did with
Pakistan? You mean
insurgents? Okay. I think you're you're
asking about
insurgents. Um, now it depends on which
insurgents you're talking about and who
they're fighting and who they serve.
There are always insurgents who can be
bought and some insurgents will so it
depends. If you're talking about the
cookie terrorists, oh I'm sure they will
help whoever will come to their aid. If
you study the history of the cookie
insurgency, the cookie terrorism and the
cookie encroachment into India, you will
see that they've always had this the
eyes on this big territory that is
mostly Manipur and they have allied with
whoever would would aid their cause. So
if the Chinese give them some aid, they
will certainly ally with the Chinese. No
question about it. No question about it.
Yeah, anime says, "Thank you for giving
us a super chat episode." Thank my my
pleasure. Thank you so much. I It's an
experiment for me. You know, I have
steadfastly said this. I've maintained
this for so many years that I will never
do super chats because uh so many of my
uh viewers are students and students
obviously can't afford super chats. But
I can see
that. But I have been told over and over
again that you know if you do super
chats and the quality of questions
improves because people are serious.
They're putting money with the
questions. So they are serious. It's not
just a random question you can anybody
can type into something. So today I
thought let's do it because I've already
done hundreds of hours of Q&A sessions.
Hundreds of hours actually literally and
I've answered thousands of questions.
All the questions are still out there.
So I thought let me try and do a super
chat episode. And it looks like I'm I'm
getting better quality questions. So
maybe it's something I should continue.
I'm really enjoying this actually. And
I've already gone past 2 hours 21
minutes. Maybe I'm going to go on until
11:00 a.m. 11:00 p.m. It looks like
that. So anyway, it's my pleasure and
it's it's great to have viewers like you
all. You know, it's a privilege to have
viewers like
you. Narendra says, "Pakistan sent
swarms of Turkish drones which India
accepted with costly missiles. Is that
an economic loss? Isn't cheap anti-
drone technology the need of the hour?"
So look it's it's it's a very common I
believe belief that people that people
have about operation tendur the air
defense component of that you know the
Pakistanis they sent hundreds of cheap
drones maybe 1,500 maybe 2,000 cheap
drones over time over 3 days into India
and we intercepted these drones with
with our S400
system or or the Akash system or the
Barak system or the Pora missiles or
whatever.
That's not the
case. We intercepted these Turkish
drones and other drones with the L70
BFOR's gun. Let's take a look at what
this gun looks like.
L70. Yeah. And this is not the So, okay,
let's first look at it. Okay, let's see
what it looks like.
L70 air defense
gun. It's a L. Okay. So, this is what it
looks like.
The design goes back to the
1940s of this gun. So very ancient gun,
1940s, second world war. But these are
upgraded L70 air defense
guns and so on. So what is the upgrade
is the question, right? So we have done
what we call jugar with the guns. We
have put upgraded radars on the on the
guns and we have uh converted the guns
into automated systems. So in the 1940s
you would have had a gunner who will
then take aim at aircraft and shoot the
gun. Today it is an automatic process.
There's no human being involved. It
automatically finds the targets and
shoots at them. And it hits the targets
every single time because we have
upgraded the gun with advanced
technology. So, it's a 1940s gun with
21st century technology and it shoots
down everything auto automatically
without human without the need for human
aiming. So, this gun L70, it shoots
shells, not bullets, but shells. And
each shell is cheaper than a drone.
Okay, we did not intercept those goddamn
Turkish drones with with with uh with
costly missiles S400 or Akash or
whatever. We used this ancient gun which
has been upgraded to to 21st century
standards to shoot down all the drones.
So who ended up losing more money? The
Pakistanis. Now the Pakistanis will try
and find some way of of you know of
learning the lesson and maybe evading
the the gun. So we'll have to adapt once
again. So that's how it goes. All
right. Uh Sam says, "Son
Chad, some people say that mid lowend
manufacturing is a thing of the past and
India should largely focus on cutting
edge manufacturing." Jam I think India
should focus on every edge of
manufacturing. We should become a
manufacturer of nuts and bolts and
become the largest exporter of nuts and
bolts in the world. We should export the
highest quality chips. We should export
everything and manufacture everything. I
think the world needs a mix of
everything. The world needs low-end
products also which don't cost millions
of
dollars. The world needs spoons. The
world needs forks. The Chinese
manufacture these things and sell it to
the rest of the world. Why can't we do
that? We should sell spoons. We should
sell forks. We should sell glasses. We
should sell utensils. We should also
sell satellites. We should also sell
rocket launch systems. We should sell
everything. So my point is you know yes
in the 21st century cutting edge
manufacturing is very important and you
are right
sir but it doesn't mean that lowend and
lower end mid-range mid-end etc
manufacturing will become a thing of the
past. I don't think so. So if some
people are saying that I think they are
kind of mistaken. every end and edge of
manufacturing is going to be relevant
but yeah it it it is very important for
us not to be left behind and we should
certainly be at the cutting edge of
technology for sure.
Rahul says, "Do you think quantum
computing can become an applied field in
the next 10 years or will it remain
research oriented only?" I think it will
become applied in the next two three
years possibly because we already have
quantum computing systems, quantum
computers. Even India has quantum
computers now. Yeah. So, we are also not
going to be left behind in this matter.
I'm I'm very happy to see that we also
have at least one quantum computer in
India and uh quantum computers I think
will definitely become an applied field
once you can sustain superpositions and
um you know
large large cubits and stuff. Yeah, you
going to I don't I think it's just a
matter of time. I don't think it'll take
10 years and soon enough maybe in 20
years you will have quantum computers
powering your laptops and and mobile
phones possibly probably not 20 years
but something like that who knows who
knows with the advances in AI anything
is possible so I think quantum computing
will be definitely become an applied
field I think it's already becoming to
some extent a field that is going in the
direction of being an applied field so I
think it'll happen soon and of course
research will continue in it research
Dadar, thank you so much sir. Do you
think you No, you say that Israel is
somehow a fully sovereign nation. Can't
even type the
name. Okay. Uh could you explain how is
it possible for such such a tiny country
or population to stay
sovereign?
[Music]
Um how can a tiny country be sovereign?
I mean when you're a tiny country with a
small population then it's so easy for
larger countries and larger economies to
overwhelm you if not politically and
economically or in some other way. So
it's very it makes sense to pose this
question. How can a small country with a
tiny population be fully sovereign? The
smaller your population the less
sovereign you should be naturally makes
sense. Now look at it this
way. Look at it this way my friends.
Prit Johawan fought two battle against
Gori or Gaznavi whoever the hell it was.
I always get confused about those two.
It was in the year 1 191 and 11 192 AD.
Right at that
time there was a guy in a land called
Mongolia whose name was Chingish Khan.
He was still going through the through
the paces. He was still struggling.
But but in a decade or so after that he
turned Mongol into a beast into a
phenomenon like nothing seen seen
before. And let me tell you during the
lifetime of Shir Chingish
Khan the Mongol
army had a maximum strength of
100,000 and that was roughly onethird of
the population of
Mongolia. So about a third or a quarter
of the population of Mongolia was the
Mongolian
army. Probably not. Mongolia would have
had a population of maybe 3 4 million at
the time but the Mongol army the full
total corpus of the armed forces was
about 100,000 at the peak of Chistan's
power which means that the the army that
conquered half the known world at the
time you could have fit those soldiers
into the Eden Garden stadium or the
Narendra Modi
stadium that tiny group of people
conquered half the known
world.
Yeah. So then does it make sense why
Israel a tiny country can somehow be a
fully in sovereign nation and dominate
so much of the world in in various ways?
It's
possible. If everybody every person in
the nation is aligned in the same
direction and working towards the same
goals, anything is possible. How did
this tiny
island, small kingdom on on a on a tiny
island, England, how did they conquer
more than half the world? How did they
create an empire where the sun never
set? Small island, tiny pe tiny
population. How did they do it? They did
it. The Mongols did something even
bigger. So, Israel also can be at least
sovereign, right? It's possible. It's a
nation that has a
mission of its own. It's a nation that
always feels that like it's under siege
that kind of helps the people come
together. Obviously, they also have uh
uh you know, they also have other
opinions. They they also have dissenting
voices, but overall the nation is very
much aligned in the same
direction and they obviously have very
high standards. Uh they believe that
they are great and they have a great
education system. They are great in
technology. They believe that they you
have to be at the top at the top of
science and technology in in order to be
a great nation. It's something everybody
can learn from
them. Okay.
Moit Kakulo says, "Do you think the
population crisis in China along with a
slowing economy will force the CCP to
launch a large scale offensive on either
Taiwan, Vietnam or India?"
Um the population crisis is something
that is a long-term problem. The slowing
economy is not that big of an issue
because China is now the world's second
largest economy. And even though the
economic growth is slowing down, it is
not negative. It is not a nation that's
in a recession. It's no
longer growing at 10% 12% per year like
it was doing 15 years ago. Now it's
growing at 4 5% a year, which is still
good growth for a economy of that size.
So I don't think the economic of course
it is also possible that they are over
representing their GDP figures inflating
the GDP figures maybe instead of 5% it's
growing at 3%. That's also a
possibility. So maybe there are issues
that are hidden from us economic issues.
The population issue is definitely an
issue but it's not going to be
u something that we will be see seen as
a crisis. It's a
longstanding issue. It's going to get
progressively worse and there is
absolutely nothing China can do about
it, but it's never going to be seen as
as as as a crisis. It's something that's
happening and they obviously would to be
resigned to it.
Um,
so what is it that could actually force
the Chinese Communist Party's hand and
force them to launch some kind of stupid
offensive against Taiwan, Vietnam or
India?
um that can happen only if they feel
that their population is going to rebel
against
them. That can only happen if the
Chinese Communist Party feels that its
legitimacy is going to be is is coming
under question. What is what is it that
keeps the Chinese Communist Party in
power? That's a social contract that we
will be the only party that that exists
in China. We are going to rule over you
like dictator dictators. In return, we
will give you extremely high living
standards and we will give you national
pride. That's the social contract. So,
because we are giving you good living
standards, we're giving you national
pride, we're giving you national
progress and so on, in exchange for
that, you have to allow us to rule you.
Now if that doesn't work, if the if if
the Chinese Communist Party is not able
to keep up its end of the social
contract as in making China great and
having great living standards in China,
then the population will rebel against
them and ch the Chinese population is
rebellious. It's not like us. So it's in
a scenario where where the population
shows signs of restlessness and signs of
dissent and disobedience. in such a
scenario the Chinese Communist Party
could could do something stupid you know
to to uh resus resuscitate its image. So
it's only in that scenario that I think
China could do something
stupid. Hershel says please take my
question. I have posted it in chat. Well
I'm taking questions sequentially. If
it's there I'll take it but anyway thank
you for contribution. I really
appreciate
that. Um okay you think you've posted it
not in the super chat. Well, you should
have posted it here. I will not be able
to find it because there are hundreds of
chat
questions. But anyway, I thank you for
your contribution. I really appreciate
that. VK says, "Will our civilization
survive because of the onslaught of
western culture?" I think it's it's we
are in a dangerous phase. We have
existed for a thou for 10,000 years. But
if we are not careful, we may not exist
in the 21st century as as a distinct
civilization because we are increasingly
westernized. We we have this tremendous
inferiority complex and Indians have
kind of given up on their culture.
Indian culture is no longer practiced by
most people. So it it is possible that
you know in the 20 22nd century there
may no longer be Hinduism, the dharmic
systems and Indian civilization. So we
have to be careful. We have to keep it
alive and we have to pass it on to our
descendants very careful. It's it's I I
am optimistic but I can see the danger
for
sure. Kunal Vishwas says how can Bharat
leverage cryptocurrency and blockchain
technology to reduce dependence on the
US dollar and western financial
systems. See blockchain blockchain
technology is something that India can
definitely leverage to in various ways.
When it comes to cryptocurrency, if when
it comes to Bitcoin, it is possible that
it's a US state department or US uh
intelligence thing. Ethereum is for sure
not a completely
um you know free floating currency.
uh bitcoin also there are there are
questions about it that maybe it's a CIA
project you know but when it comes to
the blockchain technology itself it's
it's a very robust technology and it is
certainly something that is uh very hard
to crack or to hack and
uh you know so it it it can create a
trustless system where you don't have to
trust anybody and you can just trust the
system itself the blockchain system uh
and and So if you have a global
cryptocurrency which is not American in
origin and which is not controlled by
anybody and if it is based on obviously
a blockchain technology then it can
certainly u you know if it is adopted by
lots of nations then it can reduce the
dependence of the world on the US
dollar. Uh so Barat if Barat decides to
adopt cryptocurrency and all that and
and maybe make the rupee may maybe
create a crypto rupee or
something. Um will it work? It will only
work if lots of other nations also adopt
the same thing. So if we use the rupee
then other nations will want to have
their own you know cryptocurrency of
their own country the crypto dollar
crypto ruble crypto yuan and so on in
which case we end up with the same
system. The only way we can reduce
dependence on the dollar is if the rest
of the world adopts a different currency
in that case you don't even have to
depend on the western financial systems
anymore because you know the blockchain
technology will ensure that you're not
dependent on any financial system. So I
think
it'll work only if beyond Bat other
countries also adopt the same
cryptocurrency and the same uh
blockchain based techn of technologies
only in the that scenario will this
happen you know going beyond the US
dollar.
Samrat says, "What are your thoughts on
the ongoing vocal support for Hamas in
the West and the shocking murder of a
Jewish couple in the in Washington DC?
Is Islam taking over the West?" Uh, I
think it's it's sad. It's horrible that,
you know, two people were just murdered
for no I don't know what reason because
they're Jewish. It's
terrible.
Um, and yeah, there are lots of people
in the West who support Hamas and all
that. I mean I mean it's okay to support
for example hypothetically the
Palestinian cause or whatever but
supporting a terrorist organization I
mean how does that work? So I it's it's
it's a it's a symptom of the fact that
um first of all the western western
academia has been hijacked by a certain
group of group of people kind of people
who you know the leftists who support
Hamas and who support terrorism and so
on and uh a lot of significant portion
of the US media is also kind of hijacked
by these people and that's why innocent
young people children teenagers years,
they end up absorbing these ideas and
believing they're right and then they
end up, you know, doing things that are
like this. So I it's it's terrible. Um,
so it's not about Islam taking over the
West. It's about it's about the the the
the left taking over the West and
espousing violent ideas and and and
supporting terrorism. That's the
problem. So the hijacking of the Western
academic system began in the 1950s
and60s. It happened very slowly, very
gradually, very subtly. But today, if
you go to any university in the US, you
will see that especially in the
humanities departments, non non non-
STEM departments, it's all lefties. It's
all lefties. All the professors are
lefties. You'll hardly find a person who
can be described as a centrist or or or
as somebody who on the right side of the
political spectrum. All
left. And these people they're they you
know they support terrorism mostly they
support Hamas and so on and typically
you'll find that that they hate India
and support Pakistan. So it's something
that happened very slowly very gradually
from the 1950s and60s onwards they
hijacked the academic system they
hijacked the media they they hijacked
feminism and so much more and today you
can see the consequences of all of that
in what we are witnessing here which is
terrible. Pashant says, "As an Indian
working in the US, what can I do to
serve my country back? I try to be the
best ambassador of India, but what more
and how to raise standards? What can you
do to serve your country as an Indian
working in the west in the US? You can
be the best ambassador of the country as
possible. So look
um every Indian who lives in the
west represents India in some way. And
obviously Indians are are almost like
model citizens abroad. Indians never
indulge in crime. Indians never do
anything nasty, anything that is
antisocial. You will never see Indians
in prison and so on. So that that's one
thing Indians already do very well. But
what can you do beyond that is the
question. Well, what you can do beyond
that is to be excellent and to be better
than the locals, you know, in every
possible way. So you're working in the
US, I'm imagining maybe you're in some
company, some corporation somewhere,
some startup somewhere maybe. So if
that's the case, you have to be the best
performer. That way you know the the
image of India obviously rises
and what else can you do? Let's say you
become very wealthy. I would love for
you Pashan Sharma to become very wealthy
and then you can invest some money in
India. And if if let's say you don't
become a millionaire but you're I'm I'm
sure you're well off as an Indian
because Indians typically do well then
maybe you can invest some money in India
or or maybe by the time you're 16 you're
done maybe you can come back to India
and and start something India. So there
are lots of ways of contributing to
India. The point is that uh if you want
to serve your country you you have to
give yourself time first. You have to
give yourself time to develop yourself
to
grow. You have to give yourself time to
acquire skills and experience and
knowledge and
wealth. If you are in your 20s, don't
think of serving serving India at this
point in time. If you're in your 30s,
probably not the right time to serve
India. Probably if if you want to serve
India, wait until you're in your you're
in your 40s. That's when you have really
acquired some experience and hopefully
some good wealth. That's when you can
decide how can I leverage my experience,
my knowledge, my skills, my wealth to
give something back to my country, the
country of my ancestors. And by the time
you're in your 40s, you actually have
some idea of how to do that. So
typically, it's how it's it's either by
by mentoring Indians or by by investing
some of your wealth in India or starting
a new company or something in India or
or or yeah, some something along those
lines. That's how we do it. Um there
Yeah. So that's how we do it. That's how
you can serve your country. It's a
long-term game. Don't think of doing it
today. Wait until you're in the right
actually the right position to do
that. Uh General Vladimir Put says if we
gets two seat then pass Ram Jesus
Muhammad Krishna. I don't know what that
means sir but thank you for
the for the contribution. I I'm not sure
what that means. Sorry. Vikramat says
why is no one taking Trump seriously? Be
it Mr. Putin, Mr. Nathanu and recently
Mr. Modi now who did not tweet after his
abrupt tweet while Mr. Trump has nobody
to blame except himself. He thinks he's
the greatest businessman in the
world. Business is all about
transactions.
Sure, but business is also about
reputation. It's also about playing the
long
game. It's also about being
ethical. And um I'm not accusing Mr.
Trump of being unethical, immoral, all
of that. But he has a very transactional
approach, a very brash, brusk
approach, and that is going to alienate
everybody. Mr. Modi has made it a point
for so many
years to support Mr. Trump in whatever
is his endeavors are or have been,
right? And Mr. Modi has always made it a
point that whenever Mr. Trump tweets
about India on social media or wherever
it is, Mr. Mr. Modi will very quickly
respond back with a great amount of
warmth to Mr. Trump. But after Mr.
Trump's latest misadventures, Mr. Modi
for the first time ever completely
ignored Trump's tweet about
India. And Trump, Mr. Trump has clearly
made Mr. Modi very angry. And I can
assure you that this is going to be a
turning point of some kind in India US
relations. India is not going to trust
the the US anymore. India will not be
buying your F-35. India will not be
buying more weapons from the US. We're
going to buy Russian or French weapons
now. We can't trust the Americans,
right? The Americans have shown that
they cannot be trusted. Mr. Trump has
shown that to India and he is making all
these nasty statements about India. He's
telling Apple not to invest in India and
so on. So if you have this sort of
approach and behavior that you don't
stand by the people who have stood by
you and if you approach everything is
transactional I will even pose with
terrorists because today it matters and
makes sense to me but tomorrow I don't
care tomorrow I'll have him killed off
if required but today I'll pose with him
if you're that sort of person nobody
will trust you nobody will believe your
word and nobody will take you seriously
right so that's something that will be
increasingly the case with Mr. Trump
because he has this pattern. He has this
this track record of being very very
capricious of being extremely incon
inconsistent of constantly contradicting
himself. So so what what do you expect
when he has this approach? That's how it
works. Uh phonography says what's the
real life difference between fascism and
communism? Both have a dear leader man
man dear leader managed economy and
military are the different fascists
don't hate religion. Communists hate
religion. That's kind of the difference.
Fascists are big on culture and
tradition. Communists hate culture and
tradition.
Fascists
love grand aesthetics. Communists love
miserable aesthetics. Lots of
differences between fascism and
communism. Fascism and Nazism are kind
of similar actually if you look at it
that way. Okay. So that is the
difference. That's the the core set of
differences between fascism and
communism. And and check it out. I mean
when you speak about fascism you're
talking about
obviously Mussolini the Italian
fascists. They were big on culture. They
had no issue with religion. They were
pretty religious. But otherwise they
were very similar to the the autocratic
communists. and uh and you can see that
the fascists and the Nazis got on very
well together at least until a certain
point and so on. So that's the core
difference between fascism and
communism. Um Vikramat says why do so
many contra contradictions in
geopolitics? Why so many contradictions
in geopolitics? Israel supports
Azarbaijan which supports Pakistan enemy
of India which is a friend of Israel.
Turkey and NATO and US are in NATO yet
our opponents in Syria. It's always big
picture, small picture. Big picture, we
work together. Small picture, small
details, we'll disagree. It's like that.
It's like any partnership.
any long-term partnership in in any
long-term partnership in any big
partnership the two partners will agree
on the big things on the big picture but
they but no two partners can agree on
everything so there will be differences
in opinion about how to do certain
details and you know what if you are a
long-term partner you will agree to
disagree on some things okay when it
comes to this matter okay we'll we'll
not look at what what you don't look at
what I'm doing I will not look at what
you're and we will agree to disagree on
this matter but big picture we should
work together that's how it goes that's
how the real world works even in let's
say a
marriage where you have two spouses
husband and wife do you think they agree
on everything they will also disagree on
lots of things so you know it's it's not
very contradict contradictory that's how
the world works the world is full of
inherent contradictions that's the real
world it's not an idealistic utopian
world it's a it's a real world with all
the all the messy little details and
that's how it
works. Jugen says China is trying the
China Pakistan economic corridor through
Afghanistan with Pakistan. Will it
succeed and will the US allow it or US
has compromised itself for trade deal?
Uh thank you Jagen. Thank you so much.
Look Pakistan economic corridor through
Afghanistan they the Chinese have been
announcing this every year or every two
years for the past 101 15 years. Has it
happened? No.
It's known for a fact that the US pays
the Taliban a weekly stipend of about
roughly between $50 to $100 million in
cash. So if the Americans are paying the
Taliban of cash stipend every week,
obviously there has there is some deal
between the Americans and the Taliban.
The Taliban was given control of
Afghanistan after the Dha Accord between
the Americans and the Taliban. In in the
DHA accord there were secret secret
clauses which have not been revealed to
the world. So it's pretty clear there is
some kind of secret understanding and
public understanding between the
Americans and the Taliban. And the
Taliban are serving a certain purpose
for the Americans despite being a
reasonably sovereign nation. So you see
the Taliban are pashon nationalists.
They hate Pakistan. They're okay with
India. They they want their territory
from Pakistan backa and so on. Beyond
that they want the world to leave them
alone to rule their country the way they
want. If the Americans are giving some
cash they will accept it and do
something for the Americans but not
beyond a certain point. They are okay
with the Chinese also as long as the
Chinese don't mess Afghanistan up too
much. And they are clearly aware of the
Chinese and the kind of threat that
Chinese can pose pose for them. So it's
complicated and the Chinese have been
claiming for a long time the China
Pakistan economic corridor will pass
through Afghanistan and the belt and
road uh infrastructure will also part
through pass through Afghanistan. I mean
how how many years has it been 20 years
now? What
happened not happening? The Taliban came
to power. Okay, forget about forget
about 20 years. The Taliban came to
power in which year? 2022 23 whenever it
was. It's been 2 three years. Has
anything happened? So thus far it's all
talk talk talk. I am I have no interest
in talk. When something happens on the
ground, I'll I will take that seriously.
Words versus actions. I don't care about
words. Words. Anybody has words.
Everybody has words. Words words. I want
to see actions and actions. Nothing has
happened on the ground so far. So um so
I would not be too worried about that
right
now. Uh Inferno Jes says India already
has a success story in public private
partnership. UI why can't this be
replicated for military manufacturing? I
think it can be and should be replicated
public part public private partnerships
for military and so on. I think it's
happening. For example, India probably
has one of the best drone manufacturing
ecosystems in the world today. Much of
it is private. For example, h I mean
those wonderful screaming drones that we
saw slamming into Pakistani military and
terrorist targets, those were probably
manufactured by uh through public
private partnerships. maybe may may
maybe possibly to a large extent
private. So I think we are going in the
right direction and what you are saying
is very right that we need to take this
to the next level. What's happening is
just the beginning. We need to really
really double down, triple down, 10
times down on this and and
become one of the biggest manufacturers
uh of military equipment in the world.
We definitely at least should be 100%
self-sufficient and reliant in in terms
of military manufacturing and hopefully
we can export become a major exporter
but not like the Americans who fund wars
to export military equipment. We should
we should export it to those who
genuinely need it. That's
all. Uh Yatin Kumar says how do we how
do you see towards India and Modi from
the 2019 perspective considering how
COVID was actually good for India other
events in operation Synindor? uh
operation uh 2019 to 2025 a lot has
changed. I'm not sure if COVID was good
for India. It was actually bad for the
Indian economy. Lots of Indian
businesses were ruined. Lots of people
in India suffered tremendously. The
whole country shut down. India's economy
went into a recession briefly. Uh the
GDP shrank. It went into into negative
growth which which which means that it
shrank and it was not a good time for
India. I I don't see co was good for
India. I'm not sure how you see it but
okay. I I I take I take what you say. Um
so 20 2019 was the beginning of a bad
time for India actually October onwards
COVID and all that. Uh but 2025 is a
different India. We are now past the
COVID era. We have again got back on our
feet and we are again going in the right
direction definitely in the right
direction. Uh Operation Synindur was
very good. it was um prematurely paused
because Trump and his big ego came in
the way and his need to have to have
Pakistan continue to exist. That sort of
thing. Um
uh how do I see the path that India has
taken? How do I see Mr. Modi's
performance? I think Mr. Modi will go
down in history as one of the greatest
prime minister prime ministers we've
ever ever had. No question about it.
Obviously, there are some uh things that
could have been done better. I am
obviously one of the big disappointments
is uh the situation in Manipur which is
a disaster. Uh the indigenous people are
being horribly oppressed by foreigners.
The other big issue is the fact that
there are 100 million Bangladeshes in
India at least or
allegedly
approximately what has been done about
that? I think now some action has been
taken. I want all of them out because
they are a burden on our people. What
about the Rohhingyas? What about the
cookies? about the Pakistanis I mean God
knows how many illegal infrareds we have
that is an issue that needs to be dealt
with education reforms again nothing has
happened new education policy is a joke
it doesn't really address any of the
real issues but apart from that Mr. Modi
has done a tremendous amount of good
work I mean compared to 2019 Balakur
operation sindu today it is a night and
day difference so Mr. Modi has has done
a tremendous job of making sure that we
are militarily in a very strong
position. Obviously, a lot more needs to
be done. Jet engine issue is there,
fighter planes issue is there, lot of
issues are there. Well, Mr. Bodhi
inherited so many huge issues. So, I
think he's done a tremendous job.
Overall, I think he's done a tremendous
job. Uh, overall, I I would say I'm
happy with him. Overall, I would say
that I am not satisfied that we are
doing enough. We should do even more. I
am never satisfied. But overall, that's
how I see it. Right.
Okay, Vikramat says, "Should there be an
alliance between India, Greece, Armenia,
Cypus to counter the Pakistan, Turkey,
Azarbaijan nexus, even Israel can join?"
Yeah, certainly. I think we have some
kind of military agreement with our old
friends, the Greeks. The last time we
had a military alliance with Greece was
more than 2,300 years ago. So, I think
we have some kind of military alliance
with Greece now. And the Cypress
obviously uh is happy to is welcome to
join Armenia also. We are we are aiding
Armenia. We are supplying Armenia with
the world's deadliest anti-aircraft
system, the Akash SAM system. Uh so it
doesn't, you know, you don't have to
formalize an alliance. You can have an
unofficial unspoken, unstated, unwritten
alliance. I think we already kind of
have that if definitely India, Greece,
Armenia, I'm not sure about Cypress. We
also have engagements with Cypress. So
maybe so what you mention is actually
it's kind of in the works possibly.
Yeah, maybe even Israel can join. We can
see. Uh Vidi says how super chat don't
feel like Jia attacks on education. I'm
not sure how it does attacks on
education. Yeah, of course. See, like I
said, I have done hundreds of hours of
this without any super chats and
thousands of questions. answered and I'm
told that if you do super chats then the
the quality of questions improve incre
improves significantly because people
are serious when they're asking question
and I can see that I think today's
episode has been
very I I've really enjoyed it. I think
the quality of the questions has gone up
significantly. So maybe it makes sense
to have super chats because only serious
people will ask super chat super chat
questions.
Um and and for those people who can't
ask super chat questions, maybe I can
possibly in the future, maybe in the
coming weeks, do two live streams in a
week. One could be a super chat live
stream, one could be a live a live
stream in which I will take questions
that people have asked in the comments.
That way there are no super chats there.
Only the best questions will be picked.
How about that? And when it comes to
education, I've answered thousands of
questions. You can see all the past
episodes. Everything is for free. So I
don't think there's any GIA tax and
education
there. Okay. Really now says can I isro
launches be sabotaged? Two out of two
failures in 2025. It's a possibility.
You know now nobody speaks about this
today but in the 1980s many of the
French Ayan launches were sabotaged by
spies. No one speaks about that today.
You won't even find it on Wikipedia
anymore. Wikipedia you know. But yes
there was a spy issue with the French
Aran program. Many of their launches
failed. So yeah, Mr. 88 says, "Who was
Mr. Nelson Mandela? Was he a western
stoogge just like a certain someone from
our nation?" I wonder who that could be.
Or was he a real revolutionary
leader? Well, he was a freedom fighter.
He believed in armed resistance against
apathide. He believed in the armed
overthrow of a apathide. He was one of
the leaders of the African National
Congress, the ANC. and he was imprisoned
for I don't know 27 or so years by the
South African apathide region the white
dominated apathide regime for uh trying
to fight for the for the rights of the
indigenous native people of South
Africa.
Um now was he a western stoogge? I'm not
sure about that. I'm not
really I'm not really looked into the
life story and history of Mr. Nelson
Mandela. So I'm not sure if he was a
western stoogge. If you fight the whites
and you fight the whites through violent
means, it kind of means that you are not
quite a western stoogge, right? Unless
unlike a certain someone from India like
you're saying because Mr. Nelson Mandela
tried to fight the whites using violent
means. So that's a big difference. Later
on after he was released, he espoused
nonviolence and all that because he got
what he wanted. He he got he got what he
wanted the end of apathide and he became
president. So once you get what you want
why would you espouse violence right? So
it doesn't make sense. So I think it was
very very
smart and obviously he was very
forgiving. He did not um keep any
personal grudges against anybody once he
became president. So very nice of
him. Uh Jagen says my question is why is
our government unable to deal with the
bureaucracy? After all, they're the main
roadblocks for civil development and
research policies in India. Thank you
for opening super chat. Thank you, sir.
Look, without the bureaucracy, the
government can't do a thing. How does
the government of India get things
done? You can draft policies and write
papers and things, but those policies
have to be implemented on the ground.
Who does that? It's the bureaucrats.
Now if you start dealing harshly with
the bureaucrats, what will happen?
They'll go on strike. Then the
government is paralyzed and becomes
toothless and powerless. That's why you
can't deal harshly with the bureaucracy.
You have to take it very slowly and step
by step. Especially our bureaucracy.
That's the reason. That's the problem.
I'm not saying all bureaucrats are are
bad. There are some outstanding
bureaucrats, upstanding bureaucrats for
sure. But overall it's a it's a problem
in India, right? We know that. We all
know that. So the thing is without
without the cooperation of the
bureaucrats the government becomes
completely powerless and that's the
problem that we are facing. Okay, I'm
going to take um just a few more
questions. I've crossed 3 hours. So
please stop paying for super chats now
because I may be able to not take your
questions anymore. I'll do it for
another 10 minutes and that's about it.
Hush Raj says, "Why no Indian explorers
like Europeans and Chinese?" Well, do
you know that about 4,000 years ago
there was the in sudden introgression of
Indian genetics into
Australia? Don't believe me? Maybe you
will believe web search. So, let's
see. 4,000 plus years ago, uh,
Indian Indian DNA
Australia
Aboriginal. Check this out.
Uh this is just an AI overview. Let's
look at nature.com. I think everybody
will trust
nature.com. Uh aboriginal Australian
genomes reveal Indian ancestry. Flow of
genes suggest continent was not isolated
after all. And then you can't read a
thing because it's behind a pay wall.
Thank you. Nature scientific American
genomes show Indian influx to Australia
4,000 years ago. uh some aboriginal
Australians can trace as much as 11% of
of their genomes to migrants who reached
the island about 4,000 years ago from
India and so on and so forth and so on
so forth. Long story. My point is so
lots of uh Okay, so I I have videos over
here. It's pulling up my videos. Anyway,
my point is you have Indians reaching
Australia 4,000 years ago. Now, in case
you don't know where Australia is, let
me put up put the put up the map on the
screen so that we all realize how far
Australia is and how isolated it
is. Check it out. Here's the map. You
see where India is? You see where
Australia is, how far it is. It's in the
middle of the ocean, the southern Indian
Ocean and the Pacific Ocean and the
Arctic and Antarctic Ocean. You see how
far it is? Can you reach by land? You
can't reach there by land. 4,000 years
ago Indians reached
Australia. Some aboriginal Australians
have 11% of their DNA which is of Indian
origin. And by the way, it did not say
South Indian, North Indian, anything. It
said Indian, which means we are all the
same DNA. We're all the same people.
Okay? And overall, if you look at the
statistical sample of all Australian
aboriginal people, about 10% of them
have significant like like non-trivial
amounts of Indian
ancestry. What happened there? No Indian
explorers like Europeans, Chinese. You
see, you have the problem is your
teachers, your textbooks don't treat you
the truth. And that's why my friends, we
all believe that Indians did nothing.
4,000 years ago at the same time when
Indians had reached
Australia at that time itself 4,000
years ago you have the presence sudden
sudden appearance of Indian zebu
cattle in Mesopotamia and
Egypt at the same time when Indians are
reaching Australia they are also
reaching Egypt and
Mesopotamia and around that time you
have the Yamna invasion of Europe so
let's Please, please take the time to to
research things. Take the time to
research things. Indians were the
biggest explorers, the greatest. We h we
are the original maritime civilization.
The riged speaks about ships that had a
100 oes ships with 100 oes. O A R S OS.
The Romans, they had these warships
called galleys which were powered by
oes. The os were were powered by slaves
who were chained below deck. How many
ships how many oes did the Roman galleys
have? 50
oes. The rigida comes thousands of years
before the Romans. We had ships with 100
overs in the samudra. We were the
original
explorers. But your teachers won't teach
you this. Your teachers don't know.
They're illiterate. Your textbooks won't
teach you this. That's the problem with
India. Okay. Rip power says how to deal
with deeprooted behavioral patterns
um in yourself in somebody else. If you
have deep rooted behavioral patterns
which are not good for you, then you
have to find ways of changing them. You
have to try and identify the root
causes. Let's say you have a phone
addiction like like we took in the
beginning of the show. Then the question
is why do you have a phone addiction?
what gap in your life is it filling that
you're not able to fill with something
else you to identify the deep
psychological root cause for this thing
and then you to address that that's what
I would say
um exactly says exactly when our gurugul
padi starts declining it started with
the British occupation of India in the
19th century uh the great writer Daral
he compiled statistical data of that the
British had collected
of the Indian education system, the
indigenous Indian education system and
you had the gurugal system all all over
the country. You still had temples as
the center of education in the 19th
century. That's when Macaulay imposed
the British education system on India
which was designed to to enslave Indians
and to turn Indians into clerks and
peons. That's in in the in the 19 1830s
1840s onwards that they destroyed the
indigenous Indian education system.
That's when the process started and
today we are continuing the molleian
system.
See phantom surge says fix for lack of
meritocracy and cast divisions. The
government has to end this nonsense
otherwise people will just leave the
country. There is no other fix. We can't
fix it. The government has to fix it.
How to end cast divisions? Today it is
mandatory for you to have your cast on
your birth certificate, on your school
documents, on your school living
certificate and blah blah
blah. Government mandates the use of
cast and all these things. In the
census, apparently they'll be cast.
Remove all mentions of cast from
official documents. Make cast
irrelevant. Will the politicians do it?
That will fix all the problems? They
won't do it. You see karaj thank you so
much sir thank you very much savage says
do you see China and India first of all
thank you do you see China and India
settling their land differences over
water resources annex next since
1971 I see I I am Indian-American in
Maryland no one takes India seriously
this needs to change well if you're in
Maryland nobody will take India
seriously Maryland is the is the
heartland of the American intelligence
and and community and the overall US
estab establishment, the deep
establishment, Maryland. Um, nobody
there takes India seriously. They all
still have this this 20th century
mindset. A lot of them in Maryland, in
DC, in the DC area and the Maryland
area, no, nobody talks about India.
Nobody takes India seriously. The only
nations that take seriously in Maryland
apart from the US are Russia and China
to some is Israel for sure and to some
extent France. Beyond that, no nothing.
They don't think about India. They don't
talk about India. Um now do I see India
and China settling their land
differences over water resources next
since 1971. Uh the Chinese will not want
to settle their differences with India.
They use this uh border dispute. They
use the fact that the India Tibet border
is is undemarcated as a pressure point
against India. They want to use this as
leverage against India to be deployed
this leverage. They want to deploy it at
any time that they choose to. So they
have steadfastly refused to demarcate
the border right if the border is
demarcated then there's no more issue
with between India and China but they
don't want that so the the problem that
exists between India and China is
entirely of China's making okay we have
tried our best to have this demarcated
but they don't want this so I don't see
this changing for now uh the only way
the Chinese will come to the negotiating
table seriously and resolve the
difference is if India becomes way more
powerful than it is today. For example,
the Russians and the Chinese had a big
land dispute, border dispute, the Usuri
issue. They nearly went to war in
1969 or the Usuri River issue, the
Highline, whatever that island is
called. I forget the name of the island.
It's a Chinese name. And the two nations
fought there. Hundreds of soldiers died
on both sides. And Russia had decided to
nuke China. And the Americans saved
China.
uh and this dispute was ended in the
21st century. The first decade of the
21st century by the time the Russians
had again started resurging as a power
that's when the Chinese took them
seriously. So if India and China are to
settle the dispute whatever they have
land land differences it will happen
only when the Chinese will see India as
an competitor and as a nation they can
really respect and respect only comes
through fear.
So um Prrenai says the only problem
hindering India is reservations. Now I
agree reservations and corruption.
Beyond that you know if we resolve these
two issues reservations and corruption
India will be unleashed. The full energy
of India will be unleashed. India will
be unstoppable. But you know it it
benefits some people. Reservations and
corruptions benefit people. It benefits
you we know who it benefits and they
they are in the people who are holding
on to power in the country and you know
that's the
problem. Viv says recently an Indian UFC
fighter lost humiliatingly in just 45
seconds to a young China prospect. India
needs to protein max not dal and promote
jibbing. You know Indians
uh Indians suffer from a severe protein
deficiency.
Indians think that their diet is the
best in the world when it's actually a
starvation diet. The British starved us
for two and a half centuries and our
diet completely changed during the time.
If you read ancient Indian texts like
manasa and other texts, you will see
that our actual diet about a thousand
years ago was very different from what
we have today. We used to eat a lot of
protein and today we eat dal. Dal has
some protein but it has a tremendous
truckload of carbohydrates with the
protein. So if you let's say you
eat some meat let's say okay 100 grams
you get let's say 25 g of protein with
that let's say let's say we're talking
about chicken one 100 g of chicken will
give you I don't know roughly 20 25
grams of protein and calories how much x
number of calories if you take 100 grams
of dal you will get at least twice the
amount of calories through carbohydrates
maybe twice the amount of calories
through carbohydrates and less than half
the protein
So if you want to bulk lean, you simply
can't use
dal or chana or or rajma or whatever.
It's just full of extra
carbohydrates and you will get end up
end up bloating
yourself. So what's the solution? Eat
paneer which is a lot of fat and not
enough protein or eat meat. Indians used
to eat meat back in the past. Now if you
don't want to eat meat, it it doesn't
mean that you can't get strong but it'll
take you longer. So I'm not advocating
that everybody should eat meat or
whatever. My point is everybody should
have enough protein through whatever
means works for you and everybody should
be strong. Indians are a lot of Indians
simply don't you know they simply don't
take the time to strengthen themselves
physically. So I agree with Vive
here. Okay. Ajit J says how India
counter China chicken neck as China is
there. What should India do? It's a I
think India will have to wait it out and
in the future obviously we'll be able to
widen it. Right now right now India is
not powerful enough to change the
geography and the lines on the border
right now because see if you want to
widen the chicken chicken neck corridor
you have to capture Bangladeshi
territory and you can't do that without
going to war. Bangladesh will not give
it up and you can't go to war without
having a real just cause for war
otherwise you will be seen as the
aggressor. So right now India can't do
it even though we are militarily
capable. So I think we'll have to wait
for a future date for the opportune time
because that is obviously our territory.
Historically it's always
been. Uh you said Israel is a sovereign
nation. What about Iran? Yeah, Iran is
is a significantly sovereign nation. I
would not say 100% sovereign because it
is dependent on so many things on for so
many things on China and Russia because
of the sanctions the Americans have
imposed on them. They have imposed
crippling sanctions on Iran which is why
Iran has had to accept various deals,
energy deals etc. a 25 year year
strategic alliance with China and so on
which kind of you could say to some
extent compromises to some extent their
sovereignty. So I would not say it's a
completely 100% sovereign nation. They
are kind of in a position like France
quasi
sovereign. Hershit Jen says what's your
opinions on Duvarati? Is it biased or
neutral? I have never seen a single
Dhuvrati video. Uh but the um the
impression I get is that he's extremely
anti-India. Okay. I have never watched a
single Duvati video in my life. I have
no interest in doing that. But my the
impression I get is that he's very
strongly anti-India. That's the
impression I get. Hopefully I'm wrong,
but that's the impression that I'm
getting from everybody I speak to, from
trusted people I speak
to. Dr. Ritik Patnak says are balo
people actually good or will they turn
out like Bangladesh I think Balo people
people were always targeted and had to
survive to live look everybody is good
even Bangladeshes are human beings
they're they're
also good people I suppose but as a
nation you acquire a certain identity
and a certain character and a set of
characteristics and it was our fault
that we allowed Bangladesh to just slip
out and we just let them go and do
whatever they want we should have uh
mentored
Bangladesh and steered them in the right
direction. We didn't do it. Our leaders
messed up and that's why Bangladesh is
today an enemy of India and the
Bangladeshi people they're taught to
hate India just like the Pakistanis. Now
after Balojasthan becomes free, we
should mentor Balojasthan, we should
handhold Balojasthan and take it in the
right direction otherwise it may even it
even it may end up like Bangladesh. So
it all depends on how we
approach the relationship with this
nation once it becomes free from
Pakistan in the future. Inferno says
shouldn't we come up with a punishment
to make illegal immigrants work off
their stay and charge them for the
return tickets? EU may adopt it. I think
we can certainly confiscate all their
property which they may have acquired in
India and confiscate their bank balance
and send them back to wherever they came
from penny less. Beyond that, I don't
think we we want them on our territory
for one minute extra than needed. Right?
So we should confiscate all their
property whatever they may have and on
whatever bank balance or money or cash
they may have and send them back
penniles because they've leed all the
money and property and and wealth off of
India. That's what we should do. Beyond
that we should not make them stay longer
and work. We should get rid of them at
the earliest. That's what I would say.
And with that I am at an end of today's
live stream. Thank you so much. A very
long live stream. 3 hours 17 minutes.
I'm going to end it over here. Thank you
so much. I really enjoyed this. I may
change my mind about super chats. I
think I really enjoyed the super chats.
I think the quality of the questions was
much better. It was very much fun for me
and I think I'm going to continue this.
Anyhow, thank you so much everybody for
all the questions. I hope you got some
good value out of this and I'll see you
in the next live stream which will be
I'm sure very soon. All right, take care
everybody. Thank you very much. Keep
learning, keep asking questions and keep
raising your standards. I'll see you in
the next episode. Bye-bye.